{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Odometer is to mileage as compass is to", "opta": "speed", "optb": "hiking", "optc": "needle", "optd": "direction", "ans": "D", "explanation": "An odometer is an instrument used to measure mileage.  A compass is an instrument used to determine direction. Choices a, b, and  c are incorrect because none is an instrument."}, {"question": "Marathon is to race as hibernation is to", "opta": "winter", "optb": "bear", "optc": "dream", "optd": "sleep", "ans": "D", "explanation": "A marathon is a long race and hibernation is a lengthy period of sleep. The answer is not choice a or b because even though a bear and winter are related to hibernation, neither completes the analogy. (Choice c) is incorrect because sleep and dream are not synonymous."}, {"question": "Window is to pane as book is to", "opta": "novel", "optb": "glass", "optc": "cover", "optd": "page", "ans": "D", "explanation": "A window is made up of panes, and a book is made up of pages. The answer is not (choice a) because a novel is a type of book. The answer is not (choice b) because glass has no relationship to a book. (Choice c) is incorrect because a cover is only one part of a book; a book is not made up of  covers."}, {"question": "Cup is to coffee as bowl is to", "opta": "dish", "optb": "soup", "optc": "spoon", "optd": "food", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Coffee goes into a cup and soup goes into a bowl.  Choices a and  c are incorrect because they are other utensils. The answer is not choice d because the word food is too general."}, {"question": "Yard is to inch as quart is to", "opta": "gallon", "optb": "ounce", "optc": "milk", "optd": "liquid", "ans": "B", "explanation": "A yard is a larger measure than an inch (a yard contains 36 inches). A quart is a larger measure than an ounce (a quart contains 32 ounces). Gallon (choice a) is incorrect because it is larger than a  quart. Choices  c and d are incorrect because they are not units of measurement."}, {"question": "Elated is to despondent as enlightened is to", "opta": "aware", "optb": "ignorant", "optc": "miserable", "optd": "tolerant", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Elated is the opposite of despondent; enlightened is the opposite of ignorant."}, {"question": "Optimist is to cheerful as pessimist is to", "opta": "gloomy", "optb": "mean", "optc": "petty", "optd": "helpful", "ans": "A", "explanation": "An optimist is a person whose outlook is cheerful. A  pessimist is a person whose outlook is gloomy. The answer is not (choice b) because a pessimist does not have to be mean. (Choices c) and d are incorrect because neither adjective describes the outlook of a pessimist."}, {"question": "Reptile is to lizard as flower is to", "opta": "petal", "optb": "stem", "optc": "daisy", "optd": "alligator", "ans": "C", "explanation": "A lizard is a type of reptile; a daisy is a type of flower. Choices a and b are incorrect because a petal and a stem are parts of a flower, not types of flowers. (Choice d) is incorrect because an alligator is another type of reptile, not a type of flower."}, {"question": "Play is to actor as concert is to", "opta": "symphony", "optb": "musician", "optc": "piano", "optd": "percussion", "ans": "B", "explanation": "An actor performs in a play. A musician performs at a  concert. Choices a, c, and d are incorrect because none is people who perform."}, {"question": "Sponge is to porous as rubber is to", "opta": "massive", "optb": "solid", "optc": "elastic", "optd": "inflexible", "ans": "C", "explanation": "A sponge is a porous material. Rubber is an elastic  material. (Choice a) is incorrect because rubber would not generally be referred to as massive. The answer is not (choice b) because even though rubber is a solid, its most noticeable characteristic is its elasticity. Choice d is incorrect because rubber has flexibility."}, {"question": "Careful is to cautious as boastful is to", "opta": "arrogant", "optb": "humble", "optc": "joyful", "optd": "suspicious", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Careful and cautious are synonyms (they mean the same  thing). Boastful and arrogant are also synonyms. The answer is not (choice b)  because humble means the opposite of boastful. The answer is not choice  c or d  because neither means the same as boastful."}, {"question": "Pen is to poet as needle is to", "opta": "thread", "optb": "button", "optc": "sewing", "optd": "tailor", "ans": "D", "explanation": "A pen is a tool used by a poet. A needle is a tool used by a tailor. The answer is not choice a, b, or  c because none is a person and therefore cannot complete the analogy."}, {"question": "Secretly is to openly as silently is to", "opta": "scarcely", "optb": "impolitely", "optc": "noisily", "optd": "quietly", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Secretly is the opposite of openly, and silently is the opposite of noisily. Choices a and b are clearly not the opposites of silently. (Choice d) means the same thing as silently."}, {"question": "Embarrassed is to humiliated as frightened is to", "opta": "terrified", "optb": "agitated", "optc": "courageous", "optd": "reckless", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If someone has been humiliated, they have been greatly embarrassed. If someone is terrified, they are extremely frightened. The  answer is not choice b because an agitated person is not necessarily frightened. Choices  c and  d are incorrect because neither word expresses a state of being frightened."}, {"question": "Pride is to lion as shoal is to", "opta": "teacher", "optb": "student", "optc": "self-respect", "optd": "fish", "ans": "D", "explanation": "A group of lions is called a pride. A group of fish swim in a shoal. Teacher (choice a) and student (choice b) refer to another meaning of the word  school. The answer is not (choice c) because self-respect has no obvious relationship to this particular meaning of school."}, {"question": "Artist is to painting as senator is to", "opta": "attorney", "optb": "law", "optc": "politician", "optd": "constituents", "ans": "B", "explanation": "An artist makes paintings; a senator makes laws. The  answer is not choice a because an attorney does not make laws and a senator is not an attorney. Choice c is incorrect because a senator is not a politician. Constituents (choice d) is also incorrect because a senator serves his or her constituents."}, {"question": "Exercise is to gym as eating is to", "opta": "food", "optb": "dieting", "optc": "fitness", "optd": "restaurant", "ans": "D", "explanation": "A gym is a place where people exercise. A restaurant  is a place where people eat. Food (choice a) is not the answer because it is something people eat, not a place or location where they eat. The answer is not  choice b or c because neither represents a place where people eat."}, {"question": "Candid is to indirect as honest is to", "opta": "frank", "optb": "wicked", "optc": "truthful", "optd": "untruthful", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Candid and indirect refer to opposing traits. Honest and untruthful refer to opposing traits. The answer is not choice a because frank means the same thing as candid.Wicked (choice b) is incorrect because even though it refers to a negative trait, it does not mean the opposite of honest. (Choice c) is incorrect because truthful and honest mean the same thing."}, {"question": "Guide is to direct as reduce is to", "opta": "decrease", "optb": "maintain", "optc": "increase", "optd": "preserve", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Guide and direct are synonyms, and reduce and decrease are synonyms. The answer is not choice b or d because neither means the same as reduce. (Choice c) is incorrect because increase is the opposite of reduce."}, {"question": "Oar is to rowboat as foot is to", "opta": "running", "optb": "sneaker", "optc": "skateboard", "optd": "jumping", "ans": "C", "explanation": "An oar puts a rowboat into motion. A foot puts a skateboard into motion. The answer is not choice a because running is not an object that is put into motion by a foot. Sneaker (choice b) is incorrect because it is something worn on a foot. Jumping (choice d) is incorrect because although you do need feet to jump, jumping is not an object that is put into motion by means of a foot."}, {"question": "One New York publisher has estimated that 50,000 to 60,000 people in the United States want an anthology that includes the complete works of William Shakespeare. And what accounts for this renewed interest in Shakespeare? As  scholars point out, his psychological insights into both male and female characters are amazing even today. \nThis paragraph best supports the statement that", "opta": "Shakespeare's characters are more interesting than fictional characters today.", "optb": "people even today are interested in Shakespeare's work because of the characters.", "optc": "academic scholars are putting together an anthology of Shakespeare's work.", "optd": "New Yorkers have a renewed interested in the work of Shakespeare.", "opte": "Shakespeare was a psychiatrist as well as a playwright.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The last sentence in the paragraph clearly gives support for the idea that the interest in Shakespeare is due to the development of his characters. Choice a is incorrect because the writer never makes this type of comparison. Choice c is wrong because even though scholars are mentioned in the paragraph, there is no indication that the scholars are compiling the anthology. Choice d is wrong because there is no support to show that most New Yorkers are interested in this work. There is no support for choice e either."}, {"question": "One of the warmest winters on record has put consumers in the mood to spend money. Spending is likely to be the strongest in thirteen years. During the month of February, sales of existing single-family homes hit an annual record rate of 4.75 million.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that", "opta": "consumer spending will be higher thirteen years from now than it is today.", "optb": "more people buy houses in the month of February than in any other month.", "optc": "during the winter months, the prices of single-family homes are the lowest.", "optd": "there were about 4 million homes for sale during the month of February.", "opte": "warm winter weather is likely to affect the rate of home sales.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "This is clearly the best answer because the paragraph  directly states that warm weather affects consumers inclination  to spend. It furthers states that the sales of single-family homes was at an all-time high. There is no support for choice a or c. Choice b is wrong because even though there were high sales for a particular February, this does not mean that sales are not higher in other months. Choice d presents a misleading figure of 4 million. The paragraph states that the record of 4.75 million was at an annual, not a monthly, rate."}, {"question": "Generation Xers are those people born roughly between 1965 and 1981. As employees, Generation Xers tend to be more challenged when they can carry out tasks independently. This makes Generation Xers the most entrepreneurial generation in history.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that Generation Xers", "opta": "work harder than people from other generations.", "optb": "have a tendency to be self-directed workers", "optc": "have an interest in making history", "optd": "tend to work in jobs that require risk-taking behavior.", "opte": "like to challenge their bosses work attitudes.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The support for choice b is given in the second sentence of the paragraph. Generation Xers like to work independently, which means they are self-directed. No support is given for either choice a or choice c. Choice d is not related to the paragraph. Although the paragraph mentions that Generation Xers like to be challenged, it does not say they like to challenge their bosses attitudes; therefore, choice  e can be ruled out."}, {"question": "If you're a fitness walker, there is no need for a commute to a health club. Your neighborhood can be your health club. You don't need a lot of fancy equipment to get a good workout either. All you need is a well-designed pair of athletic shoes.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that", "opta": "fitness walking is a better form of exercise than weight lifting.", "optb": "a membership in a health club is a poor investment.", "optc": "walking outdoors provides a better workout than walking indoors.", "optd": "fitness walking is a convenient and valuable form of exercise.", "opte": "poorly designed athletic shoes can cause major foot injuries.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "By stating that fitness walking does not require a commute to a health club, the author stresses the convenience of this form of exercise. The paragraph also states that fitness walking will result in a good workout. Choice a is incorrect because no comparison to weight lifting is made. Choice b may seem like a logical answer, but the paragraph only refers to people who are fitness walkers, so for others, a health club might be a good investment. Choice c is not in the passage. Although choice e seems logical, the paragraph does not indicate that the wrong shoes will produce major injuries."}, {"question": "In the past, consumers would rarely walk into an ice cream store and order low-fat ice cream. But that isn't the case today. An increasing health consciousness combined with a much bigger selection of tasty low-fat foods in all categories has made low-fat ice cream a very profitable item for ice cream store owners.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that", "opta": "low-fat ice cream produces more revenue than other low-fat foods.", "optb": "ice cream store owners would be better off carrying only low-fat ice cream.", "optc": "ice cream store owners no longer think that low-fat ice cream is an unpopular item.", "optd": "low-fat ice cream is more popular than other kinds of ice cream.", "opte": "consumers are fickle and it is impossible to please them", "ans": "C", "explanation": "This choice is supported as the best answer because the paragraph indicates that low-fat ice cream was once an unpopular item, but now, because consumers are more health conscious and because there is a wider array of tasty low-fat foods, low-fat ice cream is a profitable item for ice cream store owners. There is no indication that choices a, b, d,or e are true based on the information given."}, {"question": "Today's high school students spend too much time thinking about trivial and distracting matters such as fashion. Additionally, they often dress inappropriately on school grounds. Rather than spending time writing another detailed dress policy, we should make school uniforms mandatory. If students were required to wear uniforms, it would increase a sense of community and harmony in our schools and it would instill a sense of discipline in our students. Another positive effect would be that teachers and administrators would no longer have to act as clothing police, freeing them up to focus on more important issues.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that", "opta": "inappropriate clothing leads to failing grades.", "optb": "students who wear school uniforms get into better colleges.", "optc": "teachers and administrators spend at least 25% of their time enforcing the dress code.", "optd": "students are not interested in being part of a community", "opte": "school uniforms should be compulsory for high school students.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The support for choice e is in the third sentence \"we should make school uniforms mandatory\". There is no evidence provided to support choices a, b, and d. And although we know that teachers and administrators are spending some of their time enforcing dress code, the paragraph does not quantify how much of their time is spent that way, so there is no support for choice c."}, {"question": "The criminal justice system needs to change. The system could be more just if it allowed victims the opportunity to confront the person who has harmed them. Also, mediation between victims and their offenders would give the offenders a chance to apologize for the harm they have done.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that victims of a crime should", "opta": "learn to forgive their offenders.", "optb": "have the right to confront their offenders.", "optc": "learn the art of mediation.", "optd": "insist that their offenders be punished.", "opte": "have the right to impose a sentence on their offenders.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "This answer is clearly stated in the first sentence of  the paragraph. There is no support in the passage for choices a, d,or e. As  for choice c, although mediation is mentioned, the statement does not indicate that victims should be the mediators."}, {"question": "A few states in this country are considering legislation that would prohibit schools from using calculators before the sixth grade. Other states take a different position. Some states are insisting on the purchase of graphing calculators for every student in middle school.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that in this country", "opta": "there are at least two opinions about the use of calculators in schools.", "optb": "calculators are frequently a detriment to learning math.", "optc": "state legislators are more involved in education than ever before.", "optd": "the price of graphing calculators is less when schools buy in bulk.", "opte": "the argument against calculators in schools is unfounded.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The paragraph clearly states that there are two differing opinions with regard to the use of calculators in the classroom. Although some people may believe that choice  b is true, the paragraph does not  indicate this. Choice c has no relation to the paragraph. Choice d makes logical sense, but the paragraph says nothing about cost. Choice e is an opinion that is not given in the paragraph."}, {"question": "Today's workforce has a new set of social values. Ten years ago, a manager who was offered a promotion in a distant city would not have questioned the move. Today, a manager in that same situation might choose family happiness instead of career advancement.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that", "opta": "most managers are not loyal to the corporations for which they work.", "optb": "businesses today do not understand their employees needs.", "optc": "employees social values have changed over the past ten years.", "optd": "career advancement is not important to today's business managers.", "opte": "companies should require their employees to accept promotions.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "A change in employee social values over the past ten years is implied in the whole paragraph, but particularly in the first sentence. Choice a is incorrect because the loyalty of the managers to their corporations is never discussed. There is no support for choice b. In choice d, perhaps career advancement is less important than it once was, but the paragraph does not indicate that advancement is unimportant to managers. Choice e is an opinion that is not supported."}, {"question": "It is well known that the world urgently needs adequate distribution of food, so that everyone gets enough. Adequate distribution of medicine is just as urgent. Medical expertise and medical supplies need to be redistributed throughout the world so that people in emerging nations will have proper medical care.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that", "opta": "the majority of the people in the world have never been seen by a doctor.", "optb": "food production in emerging nations has slowed during the past several years.", "optc": "most of the world's doctors are selfish about giving time and money to the poor.", "optd": "the medical-supply industry should step up production of its products.", "opte": "many people who live in emerging nations are not receiving proper medical care", "ans": "E", "explanation": "This answer is implied by the statement that redistribution is needed so that people in emerging nations can have proper medical care. Choices a, b, and c are not mentioned in the passage. Choice d is also incorrect\u2014the passage indicates that the distribution of medicine, not  its production, is inadequate."}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\ngorblflur means fan belt\npixngorbl means ceiling fan\narthtusl means tile roof\nWhich word could mean \"ceiling tile\"?", "opta": "gorbltusl", "optb": "flurgorbl", "optc": "arthflur", "optd": "pixnarth", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Gorbl means fan; flur means belt; pixn means ceiling; arth means tile; and  tusl means roof. Therefore, pixnarth is the correct choice."}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\nhapllesh means cloudburst\nsrenchoch means pinball\nresbosrench means ninepin\nWhich word could mean \"cloud nine\"?", "opta": "leshsrench", "optb": "ochhapl", "optc": "haploch", "optd": "haplresbo", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Hapl means cloud; lesh means burst; srench means pin;  och means ball; and  resbo means nine. Leshsrench (choice a) doesn't contain any of the words needed for cloud nine. We know that och means ball, so that rules out choices b and c. When you combine hapl (cloud) with resbo (nine), you  get the correct answer"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\nagnoscrenia means poisonous spider\ndelanocrenia means poisonous snake\nagnosdeery means brown spider\nWhich word could mean \"black widow spider\"?", "opta": "deeryclostagnos", "optb": "agnosdelano", "optc": "agnosvitriblunin", "optd": "trymuttiagnos", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In this language, the noun appears first and the adjectives follow. Since agnos means spider and should appear first, choices a and d can be ruled out. Choice b can be ruled out because delano means snake."}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\nmoolokarn means blue sky\nwilkospadi means bicycle race\nmoolowilko means blue bicycle\nWhich word could mean \"racecar\"?", "opta": "wilkozwet", "optb": "spadiwilko", "optc": "moolobreil", "optd": "spadivolo", "ans": "D", "explanation": "From wilkospadi, you can determine that wilko means bicicyle and spadi means race. Therefore, the first part of the word that means racecar should begin with spadi. That limits your choices to b and d. Choice b, spadiwilko, is incorrect because we have already determined that wilkomeans bicycle. Therefore, the answer must be choice d, spadivolo."}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\nmigenlasan means cupboard\nlasanpoen means boardwalk\ncuopdansa means pullman\nWhich word could mean \"walkway\"?", "opta": "poenmigen", "optb": "cuopeisel", "optc": "lasandansa", "optd": "poenforc", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Migen means cup; lasan means board; poen means walk; cuop means pull; and dansa means man. The only possible choices, then, are choices a and d. Choice a can be ruled out because migen means cup."}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\ngodabim means kidney stones\nromzbim means kidney beans\nromzbako means wax beans\nWhich word could mean \"wax statue\"?", "opta": "godaromz", "optb": "lazbim", "optc": "wasibako", "optd": "romzpeo", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In this language, the adjective follows the noun. From  godabim and  romzbim, you can determine that bim means kidney. From  romzbim and  romzbako, you can determine that  romz means beans. Therefore, bako  means wax. Because the adjective wax must come after the noun in this language, wasibako is the only choice."}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\ngranamelke means big tree\npinimelke means little tree\nmelkehoon means tree house\nWhich word could mean \"big house\"?", "opta": "granahoon", "optb": "pinishur", "optc": "pinihoon", "optd": "melkegrana", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Grana means big;melkemeans tree; pini means little; hoonmeans house. Therefore, granahoon means big house."}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\ndaftafoni means advisement\nimodafta means misadvise\nimolokti means misconduct\nWhich word could mean \"statement\"?", "opta": "kratafoni", "optb": "kratadafta", "optc": "loktifoni", "optd": "daftaimo", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Dafta means advise; foni is the same as the suffix -ment; imo is the same as the prefix mis-; lokti means conduct. Since the only word in the answer choices that hasn't been defined is  krata, it is reasonable to assume that krata means state. Therefore, kratafoni is the only choice that could mean statement."}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\nlelibroon means yellow hat\nplekafroti means flower garden\nfrotimix means garden salad\nWhich word could mean \"yellow flower\"?", "opta": "lelifroti", "optb": "lelipleka", "optc": "plekabroon", "optd": "frotibroon", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Leli means yellow; broon means hat; pleka means flower; froti means garden; mix means salad. Therefore, lelipleka means yellow flower."}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\nmyncabel means saddle horse\nconowir means trail ride\ncabelalma means horse blanket\nWhich word could mean \"horse ride\"?", "opta": "cabelwir", "optb": "conocabel", "optc": "almamyn", "optd": "conoalma", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Myn means saddle; cabel means horse; cono means trail; and wir means ride. Therefore, cabelwir is the correct answer."}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\ndionot means oak tree\nblyonot means oak leaf\nblycrin means maple leaf\nWhich word could mean \"maple syrup\"?", "opta": "blymuth", "optb": "hupponot", "optc": "patricrin", "optd": "crinweel", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In this language, the adjective follows the noun. From dionot and blyonot, you can determine that 'onot' means oak. From blyonot and blycrin, you can determine that bly means leaf. Therefore, crin means maple. Because the adjective maple comes after the noun, patricrin is the only possible choice."}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\ntamceno means sky blue\ncenorax means blue cheese\naplmitl means star bright\nWhich word could mean \"bright sky\"?", "opta": "cenotam", "optb": "mitltam", "optc": "raxmitl", "optd": "aplceno", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Tam means sky; ceno means blue; rax means cheese; apl means star; and mitl means bright. So, mitltam means bright sky."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThe prices of petrol and diesel in the domestic market have remained unchanged for the past few months.\nThe crude oil prices in the international market have gone up substantially in the last few months.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The prices of petrol and diesel being stagnant in the domestic market and the increase in the same in the international market must be backed by independent causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThe government has recently fixed the fees for professional courses offered by the unaided institutions which are much lower than the fees charged last year.\nThe parents of the aspiring students launched a severe agitation last year protesting against the high fees charged by the unaided institutions.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The parents' protest against high fees being charged by the institutions led the government to interfere and fix the fees at a more affordable level."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThe Reserve Bank of India has recently put restrictions on few small banks in the country.\nThe small banks in the private and co-operative sector in India are not in a position to withstand the competitions of the bigger in the public sector.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The inability of the small banks to compete with the bigger ones shall not ensure security and good service to the customers, which is an essential concomitant that has to be looked into by the Reserve Bank. I seems to be a remedial step for the same."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nAll the schools in the area had to be kept closed for most part of the week.\nMany parents have withdrawn their children from the local schools.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Closing the schools for a week and the parents withdrawing their wards from the local schools are independent issues, which must have been triggered by different individual causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nIndia has surpassed the value of tea exports this year over all the earlier years due to an increase in demand for quality tea in the European market.\nThere is an increase in demand of coffee in the domestic market during the last two years.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The two statements discuss two separate statistical and generalised results."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThere is unprecedented increase in the number of young unemployed in comparison to the previous year.\nA large number of candidates submitted applications against an advertisement for the post of manager issued by a bank.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "A", "explanation": "An increase in the number of unemployed youth is bound to draw in huge crowds for a single vacancy."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThe police authority has recently caught a group of house breakers.\nThe citizens group in the locality have started night vigil in the area.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Both the statements are clearly backed by a common cause, which is clearly an increase in the number of thefts in the locality."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nMajority of the students in the college expressed their opinion against the college authority's decision to break away from the university and become autonomous.\nThe university authorities have expressed their inability to provide grants to its constituent colleges.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, the university's decision to refuse grant to the colleges must have triggered the college authority to become autonomous."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThe literacy rate in the district has been increasing for the last four years.\nThe district administration has conducted extensive training programme for the workers involved in the literacy drive.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, the increase in the literacy rate may be attributed directly to the stringent efforts of the district administration in this direction."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThe school authority has asked the X Std. students to attend special classes to be conducted on Sundays.\nThe parents of the X Std. students have withdrawn their wards from attending private tuitions conducted on Sundays.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "A", "explanation": "It seems quite evident that the parents have instructed their wards to abstain from private tuitions on Sundays and attend special classes organised by the school."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThe Government has imported large quantities of sugar  as per trade agreement with other countries.\nThe prices of sugar in the domestic market have fallen sharply in the recent months.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The increase in supply always triggers a reduction in the prices."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThere is sharp decline in the production of oil seeds this year.\nThe Government has decided to increase the import quantum of edible oil.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "A", "explanation": "A sharp decline in oilseed production is bound to reduce oil supply and import of oil is the only means to restore the essential supply."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThe private medical colleges have increased the tuition fees in the current year by 200 per cent over the last year's fees to meet the expenses.\nThe Government medical colleges have not increased their fees in spite of price escalation.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The increase in the fees of the private colleges and there being no increase in the same in Government colleges seem to be policy matters undertaken by the individual decisive boards at the two levels."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nLarge number of people living in the low-lying areas has been evacuated during the last few days to safer places.\nThe Government has rushed in relief supplies to the people living in the affected areas.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Evacuating low-lying areas and rushing in relief to the affected areas clearly indicates that floods have occurred in the area."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nIt is the aim of the city's civic authority to get the air pollution reduced by 20% in the next two months.\nThe number of asthma cases in the city is constantly increasing.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The increase in number of asthma cases must have alerted the authorities to take action to control air pollution that triggers the disease."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThe local co-operative credit society has decided to stop giving loans to farmers with immediate effect.\nA large number of credit society members have withdrawn major part of their deposits from the credit society.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, withdrawal of funds by society members is bound to reduce the lending power of the society."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThe employees of the biggest bank in the country have given an indefinite strike call starting from third of the next month.\nThe employees of the Central Government have withdrawn their week long demonstrations.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The employees of a bank going on strike and the government employees calling off their protest seem to be two independent events that might have been triggered by individual causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nPolice resorted to lathi-charge to disperse the unlawful gathering of large number of people.\nThe citizens' forum called a general strike in protest against the police atrocities.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, the people's mass protest against the police might have instigated the latter to indulge in lathi-charge to disperse the mob."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nMajority of the citizens in the locality belongs to higher income group.\nThe sales in the local super market are comparatively much higher than in other localities.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The comparatively higher sales in a particular locality are indicative of the high paying capacity of the residents of that locality."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThe life today is too fast, demanding and full of variety in all aspects which at times leads to stressful situations.\nNumber of suicide cases among teenagers is on increase.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Stress in everyday life is a major cause of frustration among the youth and is bound to lead them to take harsh steps as suicide."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThe government has decided to make all the information related to primary education available to the general public.\nIn the past, the general public did not have access to all these information related to primary education.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The government must have seen the unawareness of the people as a strong factor in the primary education programme being not successful. The step indicated in I must, thus, have been sought for as a remedy for the same."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThe farmers have decided against selling their kharif crops to the Government agencies.\nThe Government has reduced the procurement price of kharif crops starting from last month to the next six months.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The reduction in procurement price of crops must have instigated the farmers not to sell their produce to Government agencies."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThe performance of most of the students in final exam of class X in the schools run by the Government was excellent.\nMany teachers of the Government schools left the school and joined private schools.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The students of government schools performing well in the examinations and the teachers of government schools leaving their jobs to join private schools are two separate situations that must have been triggered by independent causes."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThere is considerable reduction in the number of people affected by water-borne diseases in City A during this rainy season.\nThe government has opened four new civil hospitals in City A in the beginning of the year.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The given statements are self-sufficient and depict independent events."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThe prices of vegetables have been increased considerably during this summer.\nThere is tremendous increase in the temperature during this summer thereby damaging crops greatly.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, damage to crops due to high temperature may have resulted in a short supply of vegetables and hence an increase in their prices."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThere has been a high increase in the incidents of atrocities against women in the city during the past few months.\nThe police authority has been unable to nab the culprits who are committing crime against women.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "C", "explanation": "An increase in the cases of atrocities on women and the police being unable to nab the culprits involved in the same are independent happenings in themselves."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nRural and semi-urban areas in the country have been suffering due to load shedding for quite some time.\nIf the Government is not able to overcome the power crisis, load shedding will be extended even to the urban areas.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The facts given in both the statements are clearly the result of acute power shortage."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThe university authority has instructed all the colleges under its jurisdiction to ban use of all phones inside the college premises.\nMajority of the teachers of the colleges signed a joint petition to the university complaining the disturbances caused by cell phone ring-tones inside the classrooms.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, the university's decision came as a sequel to the complaint received by it from the college teachers against use of mobile phones in the college premises."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nMost of the steel producing companies in the country have made considerable profit during the last financial year.\nMany Asian countries have been importing huge quantities of steel from India.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The increase in demand of steel from other countries is bound to enhance business and hence profitability of steel companies in India."}, {"question": "Statements:\n\nThere is increase in water level of all the water tanks supplying drinking water to the city during the last fortnight.\nMost of the trains were cancelled last week due to water-logging on the tracks.", "opta": "Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "optb": "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "optc": "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "optd": "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "opte": "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The problems discussed in both the statements are clearly the result of heavy downpour in the area."}, {"question": "Statement:  A large number of people in ward X of the city are diagnosed to be suffering from a fatal malaria type.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe city municipal authority should take immediate steps to carry out extensive fumigation in ward X.\nThe people in the area should be advised to take steps to avoid mosquito bites.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, prevention from mosquitoes and elimination of mosquitoes are two ways to prevent malaria. So, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  Severe drought is reported to have set in several parts of the country.\nCourses of Action:\n\nGovernment should immediately make arrangement for providing financial assistance to those affected.\nFood, water and fodder should immediately be sent to all these areas to save the people and cattle.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "In the break-out of a natural calamity, the basic duty of the government becomes to provide the basic amenities essential to save the lives of people and cattle. Providing financial assistance to all would put undue burden on the country's resources. So, only II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  Since its launching in 1981, Vayudoot has so far accumulated losses amounting to Rs 153 crore.\nCourses of Action:\n\nVayudoot should be directed to reduce wasteful expenditure and to increase passenger fare.\nAn amount of about Rs 300 crore should be provided to Vayudoot to make the airliner economically viable.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, for better economic gain, losses should be reduced and income increased. So, only course I follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  Exporters in the capital are alleging that commercial banks are violating a Reserve Bank of India directive to operate a post shipment export credit denominated in foreign currency at international rates from January this year.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe officers concerned in the commercial banks are to be suspended.\nThe RBI should be asked to stop giving such directives to commercial banks.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The statement mentions that the commercial banks violate a directive issued by the RBI. The remedy is only to make the banks implement the Act. So, none of the courses follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  A large number of people die every year due to drinking polluted water during the summer.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe government should make adequate arrangements to provide safe drinking water to all its citizens.\nThe people should be educated about the dangers of drinking polluted water.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The situation demands creating awareness among people about the dangers of drinking polluted water so that they themselves refrain from the same, and at the same time taking steps to provide safe drinking water. So, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  Most of those who study in premier engineering colleges in India migrate to developed nations for better prospects in their professional pursuits.\nCourses of Action:\n\nAll the students joining these colleges should be asked to sign a bond at the time of admission to the effect that they will remain in India at least for ten years after they complete education.\nAll those students who desire to settle in the developed nations should be asked to pay entire cost of their education which the government subsidises.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, no student can be bound to live and work in the country against his wish. So, I does not follow. However, it is quite right to recover the extra benefits awarded to students if they do not serve their own country. So, II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  There is an unprecedented increase in migration of villagers to urban areas as repeated crop failure has put them into precarious financial situation.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe villagers should be provided with alternate source of income in their villages which will make them stay put.\nThe migrated villagers should be provided with jobs in the urban areas to help them survive.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, increased migration would add to the burden on city's infrastructure. So, attempts should be made to make the villagers feel comfortable in the villages itself. So, only course I follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  As stated in the recent census report the female to male ratio is alarmingly low.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe government should conduct another census to verify the results.\nThe government should immediately issue orders to all the departments to encourage people to improve the ratio.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "A census is always conducted with the utmost precision, leaving chances of only negligible differences. So, I does not follow. Further, the ratio can be improved by creating awareness among the masses and abolishing female foeticide. Thus, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  Four districts in State A have been experiencing severe drought for the last three years resulting into exodus of people from these districts.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe government should immediately start food for work programme in the district to put a halt to the exodus.\nThe government should make since efforts to provide drinking/potable water to these districts", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The exodus can be stopped by providing the people conditions conducive to living. So, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  If the retired Professors of the same Institutes are also invited to deliberate on restructuring of the organisation, their contribution may be beneficial to the Institute.\nCourses of Action:\n\nManagement may seek opinion of the employees before calling retired professors.\nManagement should involve experienced people for the systematic restructuring of the organisation.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, the statement stresses that the contribution of retired Professors shall be beneficial. This means that these people's experience regarding working of the organisation is helpful. So, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The sale of a particular product has gone down considerably causing great concern to the company.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe company should make a proper study of rival products in the market.\nThe price of the product should be reduced and quality improved.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, a study of rival products in the market will help assess the cause for the lowering down of sales and then a suitable action can be taken. Thus, only I follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  The Asian Development Bank has approved a $285 million loan to finance a project to construct coal ports by Paradip and Madras Port Trusts.\nCourses of Action:\n\nIndia should use financial assistance from other international financial organisations to develop such ports in other places.\nIndia should not seek such financial assistance from the international financial agencies.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, such projects shall be an asset and a source of income to the country later on. So, course I shall follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  Doordarshan is concerned about the quality of its programmes particularly in view of stiff competition it is facing from STAR and other satellite TV channels and is contemplating various measures to attract talent for its programmes.\nCourses of Action:\n\nIn an effort to attract talent, the Doordarshan has decided to revise its fee structure for the artists.\nThe fee structure should not be revised until other electronic media also revise it.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, the decision to revise its fee structure for artists is taken by Doordarshan as a remedy to the challenging problem that had arisen before it. It cannot wait till other media take action. So, only course I follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The Minister said that the teachers are still not familiarised with the need, importance and meaning of population education in the higher education system. They are not even clearly aware about their role and responsibilities in the population education programme.\nCourses of Action:\n\nPopulation education programme should be included in the college curriculum.\nOrientation programme should be conducted for teachers on population education", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, the statement stresses on teachers' lack of awareness and knowledge in population education and as such the best remedy would be to guide them in this field through orientation programmes. So, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  A recent study shows that children below five die in the cities of the developing countries mainly from diarrhoea and parasitic intestinal worms.\nCourses of Action:\n\nGovernments of the developing countries should take adequate measures to improve the hygienic conditions in the cities.\nChildren below five years in the cities of the developing countries need to be kept under periodic medical check-up.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, the two diseases mentioned are caused by unhygienic conditions. So, improving the hygienic conditions is a step towards their eradication. Also, periodic medical check-up will help timely detection of the disease and hence a proper treatment. So, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  The kharif crops have been affected by the insects for consecutive three years in the district and the farmers harvested less than fifty percent of produce during these years.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe farmers should seek measures to control the attack of insects to protect their crops next year.\nThe Government should increase the support price of kharif crops considerably to protect the economic interests of farmers.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, the problem demands taking extra care and adequate precautions to protect crops from insects and extending help to farmers to prevent them from incurring huge losses. Thus, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  The car dealer found that there was a tremendous response for the new XYZ's car-booking with long queues of people complaining about the duration of business hours and arrangements.\nCourses of Action:\n\nPeople should make their arrangement of lunch and snacks while going for car XYZ's booking and be ready to spend several hours.\nArrangement should be made for more booking desks and increased business hours to serve more people in less time.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Seeing the tremendous response, the dealer must make suitable arrangements and deploy more personnel to take care of customers so that they don't have to wait excessively long for booking. So, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The State Government has decided to declare 'Kala Azar' as a notifiable disease under the Epidemics Act. Family members or neighbours of the patient are liable to be punished in case they did not inform the State authorities.\nCourses of Action:\n\nEfforts should be made to effectively implement the Act.\nThe cases of punishment should be propagated through mass media so that more people become aware of the stern actions.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The Act is aimed at eradication of the disease and so it needs to be proclaimed and promoted. So, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  The Chairman stressed the need for making education system more flexible and regretted that the curriculum has not been revised in keeping with the pace of the changes taking place.\nCourses of Action:\n\nCurriculum should be reviewed and revised periodically.\nSystem of education should be made more flexible.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, the situation demands making the education system more flexible and changing it periodically according to the needs of the time. So, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  The Central Bureau of Investigation receives the complaint of an officer taking bribe to do the duty he is supposed to.\nCourses of Action:\n\nCBI should try to catch the officer red-handed and then take a strict action against him.\nCBI should wait for some more complaints about the officer to be sure about the matter.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, one complaint is enough for a wrong doing. This should be confirmed by catching the guilty red-handed and then strict action taken against him. So, only course I follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The Indian electronic component industry venturing into the West European markets faces tough competition from the Japanese.\nCourses of Action:\n\nIndia should search for other international markets for its products.\nIndia should improve the quality of the electronic components to compete with the Japanese in capturing these markets.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "An escapist's attitude does not help much. The need is to compete and emerge successful. So, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  Orissa and Andhra Pradesh have agreed in principle to set up a joint control board for better control, management and productivity of several inter-state multipurpose projects.\nCourses of Action:\n\nOther neighbouring states should set up such control boards.\nThe proposed control board should not be allowed to function as such joint boards are always ineffective.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The effectiveness of such Control Boards is established by the fact that Orissa and A.P. have agreed to it for better control of its multipurpose projects. So, only course I follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The Government has decided not to provide financial support to voluntary organisations from next Five Year Plan and has communicated that all such organisations should raise funds to meet their financial needs.\nCourses of Action:\n\nVoluntary organisations should collaborate with foreign agencies.\nThey should explore other sources of financial support.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The problem arising is shortage of funds. So, alternative sources of financial support need to be worked out first. Thus, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The availability of imported fruits has increased in the indigenous market and so the demand for indigenous fruits has been decreased.\nCourses of Action:\n\nTo help the indigenous producers of fruits, the Government should impose high import duty on these fruits, even if these are not of good quality.\nThe fruit vendors should stop selling imported fruits. So that the demand for indigenous fruits would be increased.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The ideas suggested in both I and II represent unfair means to cut competition. The correct way would be to devise methods and techniques such that the indigenous producers could produce better quality fruits and make them available in the market at prices comparable with those of the imported ones. Hence, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  There has been an unprecedented increase in the number of successful candidates in this year's School Leaving Certificate Examination.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe government should make arrangements to increase number of seats of intermediate courses in existing colleges.\nThe government should take active steps to open new colleges to accommodate all these successful candidates.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The increase may not be a permanent one. So, it's better not to open new colleges but increase seats in the existing colleges. So, only I follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  On an average, about twenty people are run over by trains and die every day while crossing the railway tracks through the level crossing.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe railway authorities should be instructed to close all the level crossings.\nThose who are found crossing the tracks, when the gates are closed, should be fined heavily", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The accidents can clearly be prevented by barring people from crossing the tracks when the gates are closed, So, only II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  Majority of the students in many schools do not pass in the final examination.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThese schools should be closed down as these have become unproductive.\nThe teachers of these schools should immediately be retrenched.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Clearly, the situation demands that efforts be made to remove the lackenings in the present system of education and adequate measures be taken to improve the performance of students. Harsh measures as those given in I and II, won't help. So, none of the given courses follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  In spite of the Principal's repeated warnings, a child was caught exploding crackers secretly in the school.\nCourses of Action:\n\nAll the crackers should be taken away from the child and he should be threatened not to do it again.\nThe child should be severely punished for his wrong act.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since the act has been repeated despite various warnings, so course I would only be another warning and would not help. Severe punishment to set example for him and others is inevitable. Thus, course II shall follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  It is necessary to adopt suitable measures to prevent repetition of bad debts by learning from the past experiences of mounting non-performing assets of banks.\nCourses of Action:\n\nBefore granting loan to customers their eligibility for loan should be evaluated strictly.\nTo ensure the payment of instalments of loan, the work, for which loan was granted, should be supervised minutely on regular basis.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "To ensure that debts taken are repaid promptly, the customer's requirements and future prospects ought to be studied and their work constantly checked. Thus, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  A very large number of students have failed in the final high school examination due to faulty questions in one of the subjects.\nCourses of Action:\n\nAll the students who have failed in the subject should be allowed to take supplementary examination.\nAll those who are responsible for the error should be suspended and an enquiry should be initiated to find out the facts.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "There being faulty questions in the examination paper is a blunder on the part of school management and students should not be made to suffer on account of this. Thus, a re-test should be organised for the students and those responsible for the error be penalised to prevent reoccurrence of such mistake in the future. Hence, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  A large number of engineering graduates in the country are not in a position to have gainful employment at present and the number of such engineers is likely to grow in the future.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe government should launch attractive employment generation schemes and encourage these graduates to opt for such schemes to use their expertise and knowledge effectively.\nThis happened due to proliferation of engineering colleges in the country and thereby lowered the quality of the engineering graduates. Those colleges which are not equipped to impart quality education should be closed down.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The emphasis should be not on the Government putting all the engineering graduates to jobs but on the colleges producing not 'degree-holders' but real technical minds which could compete well for gainful employment. So, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  Every year, at the beginning or at the end of the monsoons, we have some cases of conjunctivitis, but this year, it seems to be a major epidemic, witnessed after nearly four years.\nCourses of Action:\n\nPrecautionary measures should be taken after every four years to check this epidemic.\nPeople should be advised to drink boiled water during rainy season.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The disease occurs at the end of monsoons every year. So, precautionary measures every four years shall not help. The second course of action shall be a preventive measure. So, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  Every year large number of devotees dies due to severe cold on their way to the shrine located at the top of the mountain range.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe devotees should be discouraged to visit the shrine without having proper warm clothes and other amenities.\nThe government should provide warm clothes and shelter to all the devotees visiting the shrine.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, the problem can be solved by warning the devotees of the excessive cold at the shrine. So, only I follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  There has been an unprecedented increase in the number of requests for berths in most of the long distance trains during the current holiday season.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe railway authority should immediately increase the capacity in each of these trains by attaching additional coaches.\nThe people seeking accommodation should be advised to make their travel plan after the holiday.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "People cannot be deprived of going to a certain destination merely for lack of berths. Instead it is the duty of the railway authority to accommodate all the bookings by all means. So, only I follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The Finance Minister submits his resignation a month before the new budget is to be presented in the Parliament.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe resignation should be accepted and another person should be appointed as the Finance Minister.\nThe resignation should not be accepted.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, an already working Finance Minister shall know better all the plans and resources of the Government and he alone can present a suitable budget. So, course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  A large number of people visiting India from country X have been tested positive for carrying viruses of a killer disease.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe government of India should immediately put a complete ban on people coming to India from country X including those Indians who are settled in country X.\nThe government of India should immediately set up detection centres at all its airports and seaports to identify and quarantine those who are tested positive.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, the non-infected persons should not be debarred from visiting India. So, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  There has been less than forty percent voter turnout in the recent assembly elections.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe election commission should cancel the entire election process as the votes cast are not adequate to represent people.\nThe election commission should take away the voting rights of those who did not exercise their rights.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Re-election would demand repeated expenses and following course II would reduce the voter base permanently. Instead, awareness should be created among the people to use their right to vote effectively. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  Most of the development plans develop in papers only.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe in-charges should be instructed to supervise the field-work regularly.\nThe supply of paper to such departments should be cut short.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, proper supervision alone can see the development in practice. So, only course I follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The vegetable traders feel that the prices of onion will again go up shortly in the State 'P'\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe 'P' State Government should purchase and store sufficient quantity of onion in advance to control prices.\nThe 'F' State Government should make available network of fair price shops for the sale of onions during the period of shortage.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, both the courses of action seem appropriate to prevent black-marketing in case of shortage. Hence, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  It is reported that though Vitamin E present in fresh fruits and vegetables is beneficial for human body, capsule Vitamin E does not have the same effect on human body.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe sale of capsule Vitamin E should be banned.\nPeople should be encouraged to take fresh fruits and vegetables to meet the body's requirement of Vitamin E.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The statement implies that capsule Vitamin E does not function so effectively as natural Vitamin E. Since no negative effect of capsule Vitamin E is mentioned, so I does not follow. Hence, only II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  Youngsters are often found staring at obscene posters.\nCourses of Action:\n\nChildren should be punished and penalized if they are found doing so.\nAny display of such material should be banned.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Bad things attract more and punishment after the act has been committed is no remedy. The act should be prevented. So, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  One of the problems facing the food processing industry is the irregular supply of raw material. The producers of raw material are not getting a reasonable price.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe government should regulate the supply of raw material to other industries also.\nThe government should announce an attractive package to ensure regular supply of raw material for food processing industry.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, to remedy the problem of food processing industry, a regular supply of raw material should be ensured. So, course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The Committee has criticized the Institute for its failure to implement a dozen of regular programmes despite an increase in the staff strength and not drawing up a firm action plan for studies and research.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe broad objectives of the Institute should be redefined to implement a practical action plan.\nThe Institute should give a report on reasons for not having implemented the planned programmes.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The problem is that despite an increase in staff strength, the Institute has failed in its objective of implementing its plan. So, either there should be reasons for the lackening or the plans are a failure and must be revised for practical implementation. Thus, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  India has been continuously experiencing military threats from its neighbouring countries.\nCourses of Action:\n\nIndia should engage into an all out war to stop the nagging threats.\nIndia should get the neighbours into a serious dialogue to reduce the tension at its borders.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, war is the last resort. First, peaceful talks and negotiations should be indulged in, to settle the issues of dispute. So, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  As many as ten coaches of a passenger train have derailed and blocked both pairs of the railway tracks.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe railway authorities should immediately send men and equipment to the spot to clear the railway tracks.\nAll the trains running in both the directions should be diverted to other routes.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The situation demands first diverting other trains to different routes so as to avert any accident, and then clearing the tracks as soon as possible. Thus, both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  There has been a significant drop in the water level of all the lakes supplying water to the city.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe water supply authority should impose a partial cut in supply to tackle the situation.\nThe government should appeal to all the residents through mass media for minimal use of water.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The situation can be tackled by periodic cuts in supply, and urging people to conserve water. So both the courses follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  The police department has come under a cloud with recent revelations that at least two senior police officials are suspected to have been involved in the illegal sale of a large quantity of weapons from the state police armoury.\nCourses of Action:\n\nA thorough investigation should be ordered by the State Government to bring out all those who are involved into the illegal sale of arms.\nState police armoury should be kept under Central Government's control.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, the situation demands finding out the real culprits first. So, only I follow."}, {"question": "Statement:  Financial stringency prevented the State Government from paying salaries to its employees since April this year.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe State Government should immediately curtail the staff strength at least by 30%.\nThe State Government should reduce wasteful expenditure and arrange to pay the salaries of its employees.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, curtailing of the staff strength will only increase the panic and discontent, and the satisfaction of the employees is a must. So, the Government should arrange for payment of wages. Thus, only course II follows."}, {"question": "Statement:  The cinema halls are incurring heavy losses these days as people prefer to watch movies in home on TV than to visit cinema halls.\nCourses of Action:\n\nThe cinema halls should be demolished and residential multi-storey buildings should be constructed there.\nThe cinema halls should be converted into shopping malls.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Doing away with cinema halls is no solution. Hence, none of the courses follows. Instead, certain incentives and promotional schemes should be awarded to cinema hall owners so that they could manage to draw in crowds."}, {"question": "Statement:  Duty free technology parks where foreign firms can manufacture electronic hardware components are proposed to be established at various places in the country.\nCourses of Action:\n\nGovernment should immediately implement the proposal to augment the foreign currency reserve by exporting the products.\nGovernment should not implement the proposal as it will hinder indigenous production of hardware components.", "opta": "Only I follows", "optb": "Only II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The step discussed in the statement would surely give a boost to hardware industry and help our country to stand apart in this field. Thus, only I follows."}, {"question": "harvest", "opta": "autumn", "optb": "stockpile", "optc": "tractor", "optd": "crop", "ans": "D", "explanation": "To harvest something, one must have a crop, which is the essential element for this item. Autumn (choice a) is not the only time crops are harvested. There may not be enough of a crop to stockpile (choice b), and you can harvest crops without a tractor (choice c)."}, {"question": "desert", "opta": "cactus", "optb": "arid", "optc": "oasis", "optd": "flat", "ans": "B", "explanation": "A desert is an arid tract of land. Not all deserts are flat (choice d). Not all deserts have cacti or oases (choices a and c)."}, {"question": "book", "opta": "fiction", "optb": "pages", "optc": "pictures", "optd": "learning", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The necessary part of a book is its pages; there is no book without pages. Not all books are fiction (choice a), and not all books have pictures (choice c). Learning (choice d) may or may not take place with a book"}, {"question": "language", "opta": "tongue", "optb": "slang", "optc": "writing", "optd": "words", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Words are a necessary part of language. Slang is not necessary to language (choice b). Not all languages are written (choice c). Not all languages are spoken (choice a)."}, {"question": "school", "opta": "student", "optb": "report card", "optc": "test", "optd": "learning", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Without students, a school cannot exist; therefore, students are the essential part of schools. The other choices may be related, but they are not essential."}, {"question": "pain", "opta": "cut", "optb": "burn", "optc": "nuisance", "optd": "hurt", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Pain is suffering or hurt, so choice d is the essential element. Without hurt, there is no pain. A cut (choice a) or a burn (choice b) may cause pain, but so do many other types of injury. A nuisance (choice c) is an annoyance that may or may not cause pain."}, {"question": "gala", "opta": "celebration", "optb": "tuxedo", "optc": "appetizer", "optd": "orator", "ans": "A", "explanation": "A gala indicates a celebration, the necessary element  here. A tuxedo (choice  b) is not required garb at a gala, nor is an appetizer (choice c). A gala may be held without the benefit of anyone speaking (choice d)."}, {"question": "monopoly", "opta": "corrupt", "optb": "exclusive", "optc": "rich", "optd": "gigantic", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The essential part of a monopoly is that it involves exclusive ownership or control."}, {"question": "guitar", "opta": "band", "optb": "teacher", "optc": "songs", "optd": "strings", "ans": "D", "explanation": "A guitar does not exist without strings, so strings are an essential part of a guitar. A band is not necessary to a guitar (choice a). Guitar playing can be learned without a teacher (choice b). Songs are byproducts of a guitar (choice c)."}, {"question": "election", "opta": "president", "optb": "voter", "optc": "November", "optd": "nation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "An election does not exist without voters. The election of a president (choice a) is a byproduct. Not all elections are held in November (choice c), nor are they nationwide (choice d)."}, {"question": "shoe", "opta": "sole", "optb": "leather", "optc": "laces", "optd": "walking", "ans": "A", "explanation": "All shoes have a sole of some sort.Not all shoes are  made of leather (choice b); nor do they all have laces (choice c).Walking (choice d) is not essential to a shoe."}, {"question": "swimming", "opta": "pool", "optb": "bathing suit", "optc": "water", "optd": "life jacket", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Water is essential for swimming-without water, there is no swimming. The other choices are things that may or may not be present."}, {"question": "lightning", "opta": "electricity", "optb": "thunder", "optc": "brightness", "optd": "rain", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Lightning is produced from a discharge of electricity, so electricity is essential. Thunder and rain are not essential to the production of lightning (choices b and d). Brightness may be a byproduct of lightning, but it is not essential (choice c)."}, {"question": "SCD, TEF, UGH, ____, WKL", "opta": "CMN", "optb": "UJI", "optc": "VIJ", "optd": "IJT", "ans": "C", "explanation": "There are two alphabetical series here. The first series is with the first letters only: STUVW. The second series involves the remaining letters: CD, EF, GH, IJ, KL."}, {"question": "B2CD, _____, BCD4, B5CD, BC6D", "opta": "B2C2D", "optb": "BC3D", "optc": "B2C3D", "optd": "BCD7", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Because the letters are the same, concentrate on the number series, which is a simple 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 series, and follows each letter in order."}, {"question": "FAG, GAF, HAI, IAH, ____", "opta": "JAK", "optb": "HAL", "optc": "HAK", "optd": "JAI", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The middle letters are static, so concentrate on the first and third letters. The series involves an alphabetical order with a reversal of the letters. The first letters are in alphabetical order: F, G, H, I , J. The second and fourth segments are reversals of the first and third segments. The missing segment begins with a new letter."}, {"question": "ELFA, GLHA, ILJA, _____, MLNA", "opta": "OLPA", "optb": "KLMA", "optc": "LLMA", "optd": "KLLA", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The second and forth letters in the series, L and A, are static. The first and third letters consist of an alphabetical order beginning with the letter E."}, {"question": "CMM, EOO, GQQ, _____, KUU", "opta": "GRR", "optb": "GSS", "optc": "ISS", "optd": "ITT", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The first letters are in alphabetical order with a letter skipped in between each segment: C, E, G, I, K. The second and third letters are repeated; they are also in order with a skipped letter: M, O, Q, S, U."}, {"question": "ZA5, Y4B, XC6, W3D, _____", "opta": "E7V", "optb": "V2E", "optc": "VE5", "optd": "VE7", "ans": "D", "explanation": "There are three series to look for here. The first letters are alphabetical in reverse: Z, Y, X, W, V. The second letters are in alphabetical order, beginning with A. The number series is as follows: 5, 4, 6, 3, 7."}, {"question": "QPO, NML, KJI, _____, EDC", "opta": "HGF", "optb": "CAB", "optc": "JKL", "optd": "GHI", "ans": "A", "explanation": "This series consists of letters in a reverse alphabetical order."}, {"question": "JAK, KBL, LCM, MDN, _____", "opta": "OEP", "optb": "NEO", "optc": "MEN", "optd": "PFQ", "ans": "B", "explanation": "This is an alternating series in alphabetical order. The middle letters follow the order ABCDE. The first and third letters are alphabetical beginning with J. The third letter is repeated as a first letter in each subsequent three-letter segment."}, {"question": "BCB, DED, FGF, HIH, ___", "opta": "JKJ", "optb": "HJH", "optc": "IJI", "optd": "JHJ", "ans": "A", "explanation": "This series consists of a simple alphabetical order with the first two letters of all segments: B, C, D, E, F, G, H, I, J, K. The third letter of each segment is a repetition of the first letter."}, {"question": "P5QR, P4QS, P3QT, _____, P1QV", "opta": "PQW", "optb": "PQV2", "optc": "P2QU", "optd": "PQ3U", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The first two letters, PQ, are static. The third letter is in alphabetical order, beginning with R. The number series is in descending order beginning with 5."}, {"question": "QAR, RAS, SAT, TAU, _____", "opta": "UAV", "optb": "UAT", "optc": "TAS", "optd": "TAT", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In this series, the third letter is repeated as the first letter of the next segment. The middle letter, A, remains static. The third letters are in alphabetical order, beginning with R."}, {"question": "DEF, DEF2, DE2F2, _____, D2E2F3", "opta": "DEF3", "optb": "D3EF3", "optc": "D2E3F", "optd": "D2E2F2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "In this series, the letters remain the same: DEF.\nThe subscript numbers follow this series:\n 111, 112, 122, 222, 223, 233, 333, ..."}, {"question": "Statements: No women teacher can play. Some women teachers are athletes.\nConclusions:\n\nMale athletes can play.\nSome athletes can play.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Since one premise is negative, the conclusion must be negative. So, neither conclusion follows.\nRead: Important Rules and Formulas for Logical Deduction."}, {"question": "Statements: All bags are cakes. All lamps are cakes.\nConclusions:\n\nSome lamps are bags.\nNo lamp is bag.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Since the middle term 'cakes' is not distributed even once in the premises, no definite conclusion follows. However, I and II involve only the extreme terms and form a complementary pair. So, either I or II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: All mangoes are golden in colour. No golden-coloured things are cheap.\nConclusions:\n\nAll mangoes are cheap.\nGolden-coloured mangoes are not cheap.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, the conclusion must be universal negative and should not contain the middle term. So, it follows that 'No mango is cheap'. Since all mangoes are golden in colour, we may substitute 'mangoes' with 'golden-coloured mangoes'. Thus, II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Some kings are queens. All queens are beautiful.\nConclusions:\n\nAll kings are beautiful.\nAll queens are kings.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Since one premise is particular, the conclusion must be particular. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Some doctors are fools. Some fools are rich.\nConclusions:\n\nSome doctors are rich\nSome rich are doctors.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Since both the premises are particular, no definite conclusion follows."}, {"question": "Statements: All roads are waters. Some waters are boats.\nConclusions:\n\nSome boats are roads.\nAll waters are boats.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The first premise is A type and distributes the subject. So, the middle term 'waters' which forms its predicate, is not distributed. The second premise is I type and does not distribute either subject or predicate. So, the middle term 'waters' forming its subject is not distributed. Since the middle term is not distributed even once in the premises, no definite conclusion follows."}, {"question": "Statements: No bat is ball. No ball is wicket.\nConclusions:\n\nNo bat is wicket.\nAll wickets are bats.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Since both the premises are negative, no definite conclusion follows."}, {"question": "Statements: All flowers are trees. No fruit is tree.\nConclusions:\n\nNo fruit is flower.\nSome trees are flowers.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "As discussed above, the conclusion must be universal negative and should not contain the middle term. So, it follows that 'No flower is fruit'. I is the converse of this conclusion and thus it follows. II is the converse of the first premise and so it also holds."}, {"question": "Statements: Every minister is a student. Every student is inexperienced.\nConclusions:\n\nEvery minister is inexperienced.\nSome inexperienced are students.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "'Every' is equivalent to 'All'. Thus, since both the premises are universal and affirmative, the conclusion must be universal affirmative and should not contain the middle term. So, I follows. II is the converse of the second premise and thus it also holds."}, {"question": "Statements: All roads are poles. No pole is a house.\nConclusions:\n\nSome roads are houses.\nSome houses are poles.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Since both the premises are universal and one premise is negative, the conclusion must be universal negative. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: All fish are tortoise. No tortoise is a crocodile.\nConclusions:\n\nNo crocodile is a fish.\nNo fish is a crocodile.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Since both the premises are universal and one premise is negative, the conclusion must be universal negative. Also, the conclusion should not contain the middle term. So, II follows; I is the converse of II and thus it also holds."}, {"question": "Statements: Some dedicated souls are angels. All social workers are angels.\nConclusions:\n\nSome dedicated souls are social workers.\nSome social workers are dedicated souls.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The first premise is an I type proposition. So, the middle term 'angels' forming the predicate is not distributed. The second premise is an A type proposition. So, the middle term 'angels' forming the predicate is not distributed. Since the middle term is not distributed even once in the premises, no definite conclusion follows."}, {"question": "Statements: No gentleman is poor. All gentlemen are rich.\nConclusions:\n\nNo poor man is rich.\nNo rich man is poor.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The first premise is an E-type proposition, So, the middle term 'gentleman' forming the subject is distributed. The second premise is an A-type proposition. So, the middle term 'gentlemen' forming the subject is distributed. Since the middle term is distributed twice, the conclusion cannot be universal. Since one premise is negative, the conclusion must be negative. Thus, it follows that 'Some rich men are not poor'. Thus, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Some swords are sharp. All swords are rusty\nConclusions:\n\nSome rusty things are sharp.\nSome rusty things are not sharp.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since one premise is particular, the conclusion must be particular and should not contain the middle term. So, I follows. Since both the premises are affirmative, the conclusion cannot be negative. Thus, II does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: All fishes are grey in colour. Some fishes are heavy.\nConclusions:\n\nAll heavy fishes are grey in colour.\nAll light fishes are not grey in colour.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since one premise is particular, the conclusion must be particular and should not contain the middle term. So, it follows that 'Some heavy things are grey in colour'. I is a cumulative result of this conclusion and the first premise. Thus, only I holds."}, {"question": "Statements: All good athletes win. All good athletes eat well.\nConclusions:\n\nAll those who eat well are good athletes.\nAll those who win eat well.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Since the middle term 'good athletes' is distributed twice in the premises, the conclusion must be particular and should not contain the middle term. So it follows that 'Some of those who win, eat well'."}, {"question": "Statements: All film stars are playback singers. All film directors are film stars.\nConclusions:\n\nAll film directors are playback singers.\nSome film stars are film directors.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Since both the premises are universal and affirmative, the conclusion must be universal affirmative and should not contain the middle term. So, I follows. II is the converse of the second premise and so it also holds."}, {"question": "Statements: All hill stations have a sun-set point. X is a hill station.\nConclusions:\n\nX has a sun-set point.\nPlaces other than hill stations do not have sun-set points.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since both the premises are universal and affirmative, the conclusion must be universal affirmative and should not contain the middle term. So, only I follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Some dreams are nights. Some nights are days.\nConclusions:\n\nAll days are either nights or dreams.\nSome days are nights.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since both the premises are particular, no definite conclusion follows. However, II is the converse of the second premise and thus it holds."}, {"question": "Statements: All jungles are tigers. Some tigers are horses.\nConclusions:\n\nSome horses are jungles.\nNo horse is jungle.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Since the middle term 'tigers' is not distributed even once in the premises, no definite conclusion follows. However, I and II involve only the extreme terms and form a complementary pair. So, either I or II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: All poles are guns. Some boats are not poles.\nConclusions:\n\nAll guns are boats.\nSome boats are not guns.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Clearly, the term 'guns' is distributed in both the conclusions without being distributed in any of the premises. So, neither conclusion follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Many scooters are trucks. All trucks are trains.\nConclusions:\n\nSome scooters are trains.\nNo truck is a scooter.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since the first premise is particular, the conclusion must be particular and should not contain the middle term. Thus, only I follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Some papers are pens. Angle is a paper.\nConclusions:\n\nAngle is not a pen.\nAngle is a pen.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Since the middle term 'papers' is not distributed even once in the premises, no definite conclusion follows. However, I and II involve only the extreme terms and form a complementary pair. Thus, either I or II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: All birds are tall. Some tall are hens.\nConclusions:\n\nSome birds are hens.\nSome hens are tall.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since the middle term 'tall' is not distributed even once in the premises, no definite conclusion follows. However, II is the converse of the second premise and so it holds."}, {"question": "Statements: Some papers are pens. Some pencils are pens.\nConclusions:\n\nSome pens are pencils.\nSome pens are papers.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Since both premises are particular, no definite conclusion follows. However, I is the converse of second premise, while II is the converse of the first premise. So, both of them hold."}, {"question": "Statements: Some men are educated. Educated persons prefer small families.\nConclusions:\n\nAll small families are educated.\nSome men prefer small families.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since one premise is particular, the conclusion must be particular and should not contain the middle term. Thus, only II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: All educated people read newspapers. Rahul does not read newspaper.\nConclusions:\n\nRahul is not educated.\nReading newspaper is not essential to be educated.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since both the premises are universal and one premise is negative, the conclusion must be universal negative and should not contain the middle term. So, only I follows."}, {"question": "Statements: All pens are chalks. All chairs are chalks.\nConclusions:\n\nSome pens are chairs.\nSome chalks are pens.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since the middle term 'chalks' is not distributed even once in the premises, no definite conclusion follows. However, II is the converse of the first premise and so it holds."}, {"question": "Statements: Bureaucrats marry only intelligent girls. Tanya is very intelligent.\nConclusions:\n\nTanya will marry a bureaucrat.\nTanya will not marry a bureaucrat.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The data does not mention whether all intelligent girls are married to bureaucrats. So, either I or II may follow."}, {"question": "Statements: Some engineers are fools. Anand is an engineer.\nConclusions:\n\nSome fools are engineers.\nAnand is a fool.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since the middle term 'engineer' is not distributed even once in the premises, no definite conclusion follows. However, I is the converse of the first premise and thus it holds."}, {"question": "Statements: All windows are doors. No door is wall.\nConclusions:\n\nNo window is wall.\nNo wall is door.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Since both the premises are universal and one premise is negative, the conclusion must be universal negative. Also, the conclusion should not contain the middle term. So, I follows. However, II is the converse of the second premise and thus it also holds,"}, {"question": "Statements: Most teachers are boys. Some boys are students.\nConclusions:\n\nSome students are boys.\nSome teachers are students.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since both the premises are particular, no definite conclusion follows. However, I is the converse of the second premise and thus it holds."}, {"question": "Statements: No man is a donkey. Rahul is a man.\nConclusions:\n\nRahul is not a donkey.\nAll men are not Rahul.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since on premise is negative, the conclusion must be negative. Conclusion II cannot follow as it contains the middle term. So, only I follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Some books are pens. No pen is pencil.\nConclusions:\n\nSome books are pencils.\nNo book is pencil.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "C", "explanation": "As discussed above, the conclusion must be particular negative and should not contain the middle term. So, it follows that 'Some books are not pencils'. However, I and II involve only the extreme terms and form a complementary pair. Thus, either I or II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: All men are married. Some men are educated.\nConclusions:\n\nSome married are educated.\nSome educated are married.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Since one premise is particular, the conclusion must be particular and should not contain the middle term. So, I follows. II is the converse of I and thus it also holds."}, {"question": "Statements: All tubes are handles. All cups are handles.\nConclusions:\n\nAll cups are tubes.\nSome handles are not cups.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both the premises are A type propositions. So, in either, the middle term 'handles' forming the predicate is not distributed. Since the middle term is not distributed even once in the premises, no definite conclusion follows"}, {"question": "Statements: No magazine is cap. All caps are cameras.\nConclusions:\n\nNo camera is magazine.\nSome cameras are magazines.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "C", "explanation": "As discussed above, the conclusion must be particular negative and should not contain the middle term. So, it follows that 'Some cameras are not magazines'. However, I and II involve only the extreme terms and form a complementary pair. Thus, either I or II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: All huts are mansions. All mansions are temples.\nConclusions:\n\nSome temples are huts.\nSome temples are mansions.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "As discussed above, it follows that 'All huts are temples'. I is the converse of this conclusion and so it holds. II is the converse of the second premise and so it also holds."}, {"question": "Statements: Some books are tables. Some tables are mirrors.\nConclusions:\n\nSome mirrors are books.\nNo book is mirror.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Since both the premises are particular no definite conclusion follows. However, I and II involve only the extreme terms and form a complementary pair. Thus, either I or II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: All trucks fly. Some scooters fly.\nConclusions:\n\nAll trucks are scooters.\nSome scooters do not fly.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Since the middle term 'fly' is not distributed even once in the premises, no definite conclusion follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Raman is always successful. No fool is always successful.\nConclusions:\n\nRaman is a fool.\nRaman is not a fool.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since both the premises are universal and one premise is negative, the conclusion must be universal negative and should not contain the middle term. So, only II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Some desks are caps. No cap is red.\nConclusions:\n\nSome caps are desks.\nNo desk is red.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since one premise is particular and the other premise is negative, the conclusion must be particular negative and should not contain the middle term. So, it follows that 'Some desks are not red'. However, I is the converse of the first premise and thus it holds."}, {"question": "Statements: Some hens are cows. All cows are horses.\nConclusions:\n\nSome horses are hens.\nSome hens are horses.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Since one premise is particular, the conclusion must be particular and should not contain the middle term. So, II follows. I is the converse of II and so it also holds."}, {"question": "Statements: All water is divine. All temples are divine.\nConclusions:\n\nAll water is temple.\nAll temples are water.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Since the middle term 'divine' is not distributed even once in the premises, no definite conclusion can be drawn."}, {"question": "Statements: All men are dogs. All dogs are cats.\nConclusions:\n\nAll men are cats.\nAll cats are men.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since both the premises are universal and affirmative, the conclusion must be universal affirmative. However, conclusion II, being an A-type proposition, distributes the term 'cats'. \n\nSince the term 'cats' is distributed in II without being distributed in any of the premises, so conclusion II cannot follow. Thus, only I follows."}, {"question": "Statements: All young scientists are open-minded. No open-minded men are superstitious.\nConclusions:\n\nNo scientist is superstitious.\nNo young people are superstitious.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The subject in both the conclusions is vague. The true conclusion is 'No young scientist is superstitious'. Thus, neither I nor II follows,"}, {"question": "Statements: Some pastries are toffees. All toffees are chocolates.\nConclusions:\n\nSome chocolates are toffees.\nSome toffees are not pastries.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since one premise is particular, the conclusion must be particular and should not contain the middle term. Thus, it follows that 'Some pastries are chocolates', I is the converse of the second premise and so it holds. Since both the premises are affirmative, the conclusion cannot be negative. Thus, II does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: All boys are honest. Sachin is honest.\nConclusions:\n\nSachin is a boy.\nAll honest persons are boys.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both the premises are A type propositions. So, the middle term 'honest' forming the predicate in each is not distributed in either. Since the middle term is not distributed even once, no definite conclusion follows."}, {"question": "Statements: All pens are roads. All roads are houses.\nConclusions:\n\nAll houses are pens.\nSome houses are pens.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since both the premises are universal and affirmative, the conclusion must be universal affirmative and should not contain the middle term. So, it follows that 'All pens are houses'. II is the converse of this conclusion and so it holds. Since the term 'houses' is distributed in I without being distributed in any of the premises, so I does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: All artists are smokers. Some smokers are drunkards.\nConclusions:\n\nAll smokers are artists.\nSome drunkards are not smokers.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Since the middle term 'smokers' is not distributed even once in the premises, no definite conclusion follows."}, {"question": "Statements: All cars are cats. All fans are cats.\nConclusions:\n\nAll cars are fans\nSome fans are cars.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Since the middle term 'cats' is not distributed even once in the premises, no definite conclusion follows."}, {"question": "Senators from urban areas are very concerned about assuring that there will be funding for a new international airport. Senators from rural areas refuse to fund anything until money for agricultural subsidies is appropriated. If the legislature funds these two programs, on which of the following could they spend the rest of the money?", "opta": "the school music program and national radio", "optb": "hurricane preparedness", "optc": "harbor improvements and the school music program", "optd": "small business loan program", "opte": "national radio and senate office building remodeling", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The total cost of the school music program and national radio is $1 million, the amount left after the international airport and agricultural subsidies are funded.\r\nInternational airport + Agricultural subsidy program\r\n$4 million + $2 million = $6 million\r\nschool music program and national radio is $1 million.\r\nHence, Total $7 million."}, {"question": "If the legislature decides to fund the agricultural subsidy program, national radio, and the small business loan program, what two other programs could they fund?", "opta": "harbor improvements and international airport", "optb": "harbor improvements and school music program", "optc": "hurricane preparedness and school music program", "optd": "hurricane preparedness and international airport", "opte": "harbor improvements and hurricane preparedness", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The only two programs that total 1.5 million dollars are the harbor improvements and school music program."}, {"question": "If the legislature decides to fund the agricultural subsidy program, national radio, and the small business loan program, the only other single program that can be funded is", "opta": "hurricane preparedness.", "optb": "harbor improvements.", "optc": "school music program.", "optd": "senate office building remodeling.", "opte": "international airport.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The total of the three programs (2 million + 0.5 million + 3 million) is 5.5 million. That leaves 1.5 million (7 million - 5.5 million), and the only single program needing that amount is the senate office building remodeling."}, {"question": "Tanya is older than Eric.\nCliff is older than Tanya.\nEric is older than Cliff.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "opta": "true", "optb": "false", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Because the first two statements are true, Eric is the  youngest of the three, so the third statement must be false."}, {"question": "Blueberries cost more than strawberries.\nBlueberries cost less than raspberries.\nRaspberries cost more than strawberries and blueberries.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "opta": "true", "optb": "false", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Because the first two statements are true, raspberries are the most expensive of the three."}, {"question": "All the trees in the park are flowering trees.\nSome of the trees in the park are dogwoods.\nAll dogwoods in the park are flowering trees.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "opta": "true", "optb": "false", "ans": "A", "explanation": "All of the trees in the park are flowering trees, So all dogwoods in the park are flowering trees."}, {"question": "Mara runs faster than Gail.\nLily runs faster than Mara.\nGail runs faster than Lily.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "opta": "true", "optb": "false", "ans": "B", "explanation": "We know from the first two statements that Lily runs fastest. Therefore, the third statement must be false."}, {"question": "Apartments in the Riverdale Manor cost less than apartments in The Gaslight Commons.\nApartments in the Livingston Gate cost more than apartments in the The Gaslight Commons.\nOf the three apartment buildings, the Livingston Gate costs the most.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "opta": "true", "optb": "false", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since the Gaslight Commons costs more than the Riverdale Manor and the Livingston Gate costs more than the Gaslight Commons, it is true that the Livingston Gate costs the most."}, {"question": "The Kingston Mall has more stores than the Galleria.\nThe Four Corners Mall has fewer stores than the Galleria.\nThe Kingston Mall has more stores than the Four Corners Mall.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "opta": "true", "optb": "false", "ans": "A", "explanation": "From the first two statements, you know that the Kingston Mall has the most stores, so the Kingston Mall would have more stores than the Four Corners Mall."}, {"question": "All the tulips in Zoe's garden are white.\nAll the pansies in Zoe's garden are yellow.\nAll the flowers in Zoe's garden are either white or yellow\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "opta": "true", "optb": "false", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The first two statements give information about Zoe's  tulips and pansies. Information about any other kinds of flowers cannot be determined."}, {"question": "During the past year, Josh saw more movies than Stephen.\nStephen saw fewer movies than Darren.\nDarren saw more movies than Josh.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "opta": "true", "optb": "false", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Because the first two sentences are true, both Josh and Darren saw more movies than Stephen. However, it is uncertain as to whether \nDarren saw more movies than Josh."}, {"question": "Rover weighs less than Fido.\nRover weighs more than Boomer.\nOf the three dogs, Boomer weighs the least.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "opta": "true", "optb": "false", "ans": "A", "explanation": "According to the first two statements, Fido weighs  the most and Boomer weighs the least."}, {"question": "All the offices on the 9th floor have wall-to-wall carpeting.\nNo wall-to-wall carpeting is pink.\nNone of the offices on the 9th floor has pink wall-to-wall carpeting.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "opta": "true", "optb": "false", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If no wall-to-wall carpeting is pink and all the offices have wall-to-wall carpeting, none of the offices has pink wall-to-wall carpeting."}, {"question": "Class A has a higher enrollment than Class B.\nClass C has a lower enrollment than Class B.\nClass A has a lower enrollment than Class C.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "opta": "true", "optb": "false", "ans": "B", "explanation": "From the first two statements, we know that of the three classes, Class A has the highest enrollment, so the third statement must be false."}, {"question": "Eileen is planning a special birthday dinner for her husband's 35th birthday. She wants the evening to be memorable, but her husband is a simple man who would rather be in jeans at a baseball game than in a suit at a fancy restaurant. Which restaurant below should Eileen choose?", "opta": "Alfredo's offers fine Italian cuisine and an elegant Tuscan decor. Patrons will feel as though they've spent the evening in a luxurious Italian villa.", "optb": "Pancho's Mexican Buffet is an all-you-can-eat family style smorgasbord with the best tacos in town.", "optc": "The Parisian Bistro is a four-star French restaurant where guests are treated like royalty. Chef Dilbert Olay is famous for his beef bourguignon.", "optd": "Marty's serves delicious, hearty meals in a charming setting reminiscent of a baseball clubhouse in honor of the owner,Marty Lester, a former major league baseball all-star.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Since Eileen's husband does not enjoy fancy restaurants, choices a and c can be ruled out. Choice b, although casual, doesn't sound as though it would be the kind of special and memorable evening that Eileen is looking for. Choice d, which is owned by a former baseball star  and is described as \"charming\" and \"reminiscent of a baseball clubhouse\", sounds perfect for Eileen's husband, who is described as a baseball fan and a man with simple tastes."}, {"question": "The film director wants an actress for the lead role of Lucy who perfectly fits the description that appears in the original screenplay. He is not willing to consider actresses who do not resemble the character as she is described in the screenplay, no matter how talented they are. The screenplay describes Lucy as an average-sized, forty  something redhead, with deep brown eyes, very fair skin, and a brilliant smile. The casting agent has four actresses in mind.\n Actress #1 is a stunning red-haired beauty who is 5'9\" and in her mid-twenties. Her eyes are brown and she has an olive complexion.\nActress #2 has red hair, big brown eyes, and a fair complexion. She is in her mid-forties and is 5'5\".\nActress #3 is 5'4\" and of medium build. She has red hair, brown eyes, and is in her early forties.\nActress #4 is a blue-eyed redhead in her early thirties. She's of very slight build and stands at 5'.", "opta": "1, 2", "optb": "2, 3", "optc": "1, 4", "optd": "2, 4", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Actresses #2 and #3 possess most of the required traits. They both have red hair and brown eyes, are average-sized, and are in their forties. Actress #1 is very tall and is only in her mid-twenties. She also has an olive complexion. Actress #4 is of very slight build and is in her early thirties. She also has blue eyes."}, {"question": "The school principal has received complaints from parents about bullying in the school yard during recess. He wants to investigate and end this situation as soon as possible, so he has asked the recess aides to watch closely. Which situation should the recess aides report to the principal?", "opta": "A girl is sitting glumly on a bench reading a book and not interacting with her peers.", "optb": "Four girls are surrounding another girl and seem to have possession of her backpack.", "optc": "Two boys are playing a one-on-one game of basketball and are arguing over the last basket scored.", "optd": "Three boys are huddled over a handheld video game, which isn't supposed to be on school grounds.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Seeing four girls surrounding another girl, while in possession of her backpack, is the most suspicious of the incidents described."}, {"question": "Mrs. Carson took a taxi to meet her three friends for lunch. They were waiting for her outside the restaurant when she pulled up in the car. She was so excited to see her friends that she left her tote bag in the taxi. As the taxi pulled away, she and her friends took notice of the license plate number so they would be able to identify the car when they called the taxi company. \r\n#1: The four women seem to agree that the plate starts out with the letter J.\n#2: Three of them agree that the plate ends with 12L.\n#3: Three of them think that the second letter is X, and a different three think that the third letter is K.\r\nThe four license plate numbers below represent what each of the four women thinks she saw. Which one is most likely the license plate number of the taxi?", "opta": "JXK 12L", "optb": "JYK 12L", "optc": "JXK 12I", "optd": "JXX 12L", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The four women seem to agree that the plate starts out with the letter J. Three of them agree that the plate ends with 12L. Three of them think that the second letter is X, and a different three think that the third letter is K. The plate description that has all of these common elements  is \"Option A\"."}, {"question": "Zachary has invited his three buddies over to watch the basketball game on his wide-screen television. They are all hungry, but no one wants to leave to get food. Just as they are arguing about who should make the food run, a commercial comes on for a local pizze-ria that delivers. The phone number flashes on the screen briefly and they all try to remember it. By the time Zachary grabs a pen and paper, each of them recollects a different number.\r\n#1: All of the men agree that the first three numbers are 995.\n#2: Three of them agree that the fourth number is 9.\n#3: Three agree that the fifth number is 2.\n#4: Three agree that the sixth number is 6; three others agree that the seventh number is also 6.\r\n Which of the numbers is most likely the telephone number of the pizzeria?", "opta": "995-9266", "optb": "995-9336", "optc": "995-9268", "optd": "995-8266", "ans": "A", "explanation": "All of the men agree that the first three numbers are  995. Three of them agree that the fourth number is 9. Three agree that the fifth number is 2. Three agree that the sixth number is 6; three others agree that the seventh number is also 6. \"Option A\" is the best choice because it is made up  of the numbers that most of the men agree they saw."}, {"question": "Mark is working with a realtor to find a location for the toy store he plans to open in his town. He is looking for a place that is either in, or not too far from, the center of town and one that would attract the right kind of foot traffic. Which of the following locations should Mark's realtor call to his attention?", "opta": "a storefront in a new high-rise building near the train station in the center of town whose occupants are mainly young, childless professionals who use the train to commute to their offices each day.", "optb": "a little shop three blocks away from the town's main street, located across the street from an elementary school and next door to an ice cream store", "optc": "a stand-alone storefront on a quiet residential street ten blocks away from the town's center", "optd": "a storefront in a small strip mall located on the outskirts of town that is also occupied by a pharmacy and a dry cleaner", "ans": "B", "explanation": "This option is both near the center of town and in a location (near a school and an ice cream store) where children and their parents are sure to be around. This is the only option that meets both of Mark's requirements."}, {"question": "The neighborhood block association has received many complaints about people knocking on doors and soliciting money for an unknown charity organization even though door-to-door solicitation is prohibited by local laws. Three residents have provided descriptions of individuals who have come to their door asking for money.\nSolicitor #1 is a white male, 20-25 years old,\n5'9\", 145 pounds, with very short brown hair.\nHe was wearing a dark blue suit and carrying\na brown leather briefcase.\nSolicitor #2 is a white male, 25-30 years old,\n6'2\", 200 pounds, with a shaved-head. He was\nwearing a red T-shirt and jeans.\nSolicitor #3 is a white male, approximately\n23 years old, 5'10\", slight build, with short\nbrown hair. He was wearing a blue suit.\nThree days after the block association meet-\ning, a resident noticed a man knocking on\ndoors in the neighborhood and phoned the\npolice to report the illegal activity. This solic-\nitor was described as follows:\nSolicitor #4 is a white male, 22 years old, 140\npounds, about 5'10\", with short brown hair.\nHe was carrying a briefcase and wearing a\ndark suit.\nBased on this description, which of the three\nsolicitations was also likely carried out by\nSolicitor #4?", "opta": "#1, #2, and #3", "optb": "#1, but not #2 and #3", "optc": "#1 and #3, but not #2", "optd": "#1 and #2, but not #3", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The solicitor described as #2 has a shaved head and  is much taller and heavier than the solicitors described as #1 and #3. Therefore, choices a and d, which include #2, can be ruled out. Solicitors #1, #3, and #4 have such similar descriptions that the correct answer is clearly choice c."}, {"question": "Rita, an accomplished pastry chef who is well known for her artistic and exquisite wedding cakes, opened a bakery one year ago and is surprised that business has been so slow. A consultant she hired to conduct market research has reported that the local population doesn't think of her shop as one they would visit on a daily basis but rather a place they'd visit if they were celebrating a special occasion. Which of the following strategies should Rita employ to increase her daily business?", "opta": "making coupons available that entitle the coupon holder to receive a 25% discount on wedding, anniversary, or birthday cakes", "optb": "exhibiting at the next Bridal Expo and having pieces of one of her wedding cakes available for tasting", "optc": "placing a series of ads in the local newspaper that advertise the wide array of breads", "optd": "moving the bakery to the other side of town", "ans": "C", "explanation": "This is the only option that would encourage people to think of the bakery as a shop they would visit regularly and not just on special occasions."}, {"question": "Dr. Miller has a busy pediatric dentistry practice and she needs a skilled, reliable hygienist to keep things running smoothly. The last two people she hired were recommended by top dentists in the area, but they each lasted less than one month. She is now in desperate need of a hygienist who can competently handle the specific challenges of her practice. Which one of the following candidates should Dr. Miller consider most seriously?", "opta": "Marilyn has been a hygienist for fifteen years, and her current employer, who is about to retire, says she is the best in the business. The clientele she has worked with consists of some of the wealthiest and most powerful citizens in the county.", "optb": "Lindy recently graduated at the top of her class from one of the best dental hygiene programs in the state. Prior to becoming a dental hygienist, Lindy spent two years working in a day care center.", "optc": "James has worked as a dental hygienist for three years in a public health clinic. He is very interested in securing a position in a private dental office.", "optd": "Kathy is an experienced and highly recommended dental hygienist who is also finishing up a degree in early childhood education, which she hopes will get her a job as a preschool teacher. She is eager to find a job in a pediatric practice, since she has always wanted to work with children.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The situation described indicates that Dr. Miller's  practice presents some specific challenges, namely that it is a busy environment with a child clientele. There is also some indication that even highly recommended, experienced hygienists might not be cut out for Dr. Miller's office. There is nothing to suggest that Marilyn (choice a) or James (choice c) would be a good fit for Dr.Miller's practice. Kathy (choice d) has experience and she  is also interested in working with children. However, the fact that she hopes  to become a preschool teacher in the not-too-distant future indicates that she might not be the kind of committed, long-term employee that Dr. Miller needs. Lindy (choice b), with her hands-on experience working with children as well as  a degree from a prestigious dental hygiene program, is the most attractive candidate for the position based on the situation described"}, {"question": "Mrs. Jansen recently moved to Arizona. She wants to fill her new backyard with flowering plants. Although she is an experienced gardener, she isn't very well-versed in what plants will do well in the Arizona climate. Also, there is a big tree in her backyard making for shady conditions and she isn't sure what plants will thrive without much direct sunlight. Her favorite gardening catalog offers several backyard seed packages. Which one should Mrs. Jansen choose?", "opta": "The Rainbow Collection is ideal for North-east gardens. It includes a variety of colorful perennials that thrive in cool, moist conditions.", "optb": "The Greenhouse Collection will blossom year after year if planted in brightly lit locations and watered regularly.", "optc": "The Treehouse Collection will provide lush green plants with delicate colorful flowers that thrive in shady and partially shady locations.", "optd": "The Oasis Collection includes a variety of perennials that thrive in dry climates and bright sunlight.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The Treehouse Collection is the only package that can thrive in shady locations. Choice a requires a Northeastern climate. Choices b and d require bright sunlight."}, {"question": "Applying for Seasonal Employment occurs when a person requests to be considered for a job that is dependent on a particular season or time of year. Which situation below is the best example of Applying for Seasonal Employment?", "opta": "The ski instructors at Top of the Peak Ski School work from December through March.", "optb": "Matthew prefers jobs that allow him to work outdoors.", "optc": "Lucinda makes an appointment with the beach resort restaurant manager to interview for the summer waitressing position that was advertised in the newspaper.", "optd": "Doug's ice cream shop stays open until 11 p.m. during the summer months.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Although the ski instructors at Top of the Peak Ski School do work seasonally, choice a does not describe anyone  applying for seasonal employment. In choice b, the statement that Matthew likes to work outdoors tells us nothing about seasonal employment or someone applying for it. And although choice d describes a business with seasonal hours, it does not describe a person applying for seasonal work. Choice c, on the other hand, very specifically depicts a person, Lucinda, who is applying for a job as a summer waitress at a beach resort, which is dependent upon a particular season of the year."}, {"question": "Violating an Apartment Lease occurs when a tenant does something prohibited by the legally binding document that he or she has signed with a landlord. Which situation below is the best example of Violating an Apartment Lease?", "opta": "Tim has decided to move to another city, so he calls his landlord to tell him that he is not interested in renewing his lease when it expires next month.", "optb": "Valerie recently lost her job and, for the last three months, has neglected to pay her landlord the monthly rent they agreed upon in writing when she moved into her apartment eight months ago.", "optc": "Mark writes a letter to his landlord that lists numerous complaints about the apartment he has agreed to rent for two years.", "optd": "Leslie thinks that her landlord is neglecting the building in which she rents an apartment. She calls her attorney to ask for advice.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Valerie signed a legally binding document that requires her to pay a monthly rent for her apartment and she has failed to do this for the last three months. Therefore, she has violated her apartment lease."}, {"question": "An Informal Gathering occurs when a group of people get together in a casual, relaxed manner. Which situation below is the best example of an Informal Gathering?", "opta": "The book club meets on the first Thursday evening of every month.", "optb": "After finding out about his promotion, Jeremy and a few coworkers decide to go out for a quick drink after work.", "optc": "Mary sends out 25 invitations for the bridal shower she is giving for her sister.", "optd": "Whenever she eats at the Mexican restaurant, Clara seems to run into Peter.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "After getting some good news, Jeremy and a few friends casually get together for a drink after work, thereby having an informal gathering. Choices a and c describe more formal types of gatherings. Choice d describes a chance or coincidental kind of meeting."}, {"question": "People speculate when they consider a situation and assume something to be true based on inconclusive evidence. Which situation below is the best example of Speculation ?", "opta": "Francine decides that it would be appropriate to wear jeans to her new office on Friday after reading about \"Casual Fridays\" in her employee handbook.", "optb": "Mary spends thirty minutes sitting in traffic and wishes that she took the train instead of driving.", "optc": "After consulting several guidebooks and her travel agent, Jennifer feels confident that the hotel she has chosen is first-rate.", "optd": "When Emily opens the door in tears, Theo guesses that she's had a death in her family.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "This is the only situation in which someone makes an assumption that is not based on conclusive evidence. Choices a and c reflect situations in which assumptions are made based on evidence. In choice b, Mary is not assuming anything to be true. She is simply wishing that she'd made a different decision."}, {"question": "Posthumous Publication occurs when a book is published after the author's death. Which situation below is the best example of Posthumous Publication ?", "opta": "Richard's illness took his life before he was able to enjoy the amazing early reviews of his novel.", "optb": "Melissa's publisher cancels her book contract after she fails to deliver the manuscript on time.", "optc": "Clarence never thought he'd live to see the third book in his trilogy published.", "optd": "Elizabeth is honored with a prestigious literary award for her writing career and her daughter accepts the award on behalf of her deceased mother.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Although choice d also mentions a writer who has died, it does not state that one of the writer's books was published after her death, only that she received an award. Choice  a states that Richard wasn't around  to see the early reviews of his novel, therefore implying that Richard died before the book was published. The other two options depict living writers."}, {"question": "A Guarantee is a promise or assurance that attests to the quality of a product that is either (1) given in writing by the manufacturer or (2) given verbally by the person selling the product. Which situation below is the best example of a Guarantee?", "opta": "Melissa purchases a DVD player with the highest consumer ratings in its category.", "optb": "The salesperson advises Curt to be sure that he buys an air conditioner with a guarantee.", "optc": "The local auto body shop specializes in refurbishing and selling used cars.", "optd": "Lori buys a used digital camera from her coworker who says that she will refund Lori's money if the camera's performance is not of the highest quality.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Choices a, b, and c do not describe situations in which a product is guaranteed. Only choice d reflects a situation in which a seller attests to the quality of a product by giving the buyer a promise or assurance about its quality."}, {"question": "The rules of baseball state that a batter Legally Completes His Time at Bat when he is put out or becomes a base runner. Which situation below is the best example of a batter Legally Completing His Time at Bat?", "opta": "Jared's blooper over the head of the short-stop puts him in scoring position.", "optb": "The umpire calls a strike, even though the last pitch was way outside.", "optc": "The pitcher throws his famous knuckleball, Joe swings and misses, and the umpire calls a strike.", "optd": "The count is two balls and two strikes as Mario waits for the next pitch.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The fact that Jared is in scoring position due to his  blooper indicates that he has hit the ball and is now a base runner; therefore, he has legally completed his time at bat. Choices b and c both describe situations in which a strike is called, but they do not state that the batter has been put out or that he is now a base runner. Choice d describes a situation in which the batter, Mario, is still at the plate waiting for the  next pitch."}, {"question": "Erratic Behavior occurs when an individual acts in a manner that lacks consistency, regularity, and uniformity. Which situation below is the best example of Erratic Behavior?", "opta": "Julia cannot contain her anger whenever the subject of local politics is discussed.", "optb": "Martin has just been told that he is being laid off. Before leaving his supervisor's office, he punches a hole in the door.", "optc": "Rhonda has visited the dealership several times, but she still cannot decide which car to buy.", "optd": "In the past month, Jeffrey, who has been a model employee for three years, has repeatedly called in sick, forgotten important meetings, and been verbally abusive to colleagues.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Jeffrey's recent behavior is clearly inconsistent and irregular."}, {"question": "A Tiebreaker is an additional contest or period of play designed to establish a winner among tied contestants. Which situation below is the best example of a Tiebreaker?", "opta": "At halftime, the score is tied at 28.", "optb": "Mary and Megan have each scored three goals in the game.", "optc": "The referee tosses a coin to decide which team will have possession of the ball first.", "optd": "The Sharks and the Bears each finished with 14 points, and they are now battling it out in a five-minute overtime.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "This is the only choice that indicates that an additional period of play is taking place to determine the winner of a game that ended in a tie."}, {"question": "In the Maple Hill school district, a Five-Day Suspension occurs when a student is not permitted to attend school for five days for  (1) physically assaulting another student, a teacher, or a school employee or (2) willfully destructing or defacing school property. Which situation below is the best example of a Five-Day Suspension?", "opta": "Lillian gets caught cheating on a math test for the second time and is suspended from school.", "optb": "Marc is asked to leave the classroom due to his constant disruptions.", "optc": "Franny uses spray paint to write derogatory comments on the locker room wall and she is given a suspension.", "optd": "Ms. Farmer tells her class that students who fail the midterm exam will be expected to stay after school for tutoring help.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Although choices a and  c both describe suspensions, only choice c describes a suspension that is the result of one of the two scenarios given in the definition of a five-day suspension (physical assault or destructing or defacing school property). Therefore, we can assume that Franny's suspension, which is the result of spray painting school property, will be a five-day suspension. Since  the definition doesn't provide any information about suspensions for cheating, we can assume that Lillian's suspension does not fall into the five-day suspension category."}, {"question": "It is appropriate to compensate someone if you have damaged his or her property in some way. This is called Restitution. Which situation below is the best example of Restitution?", "opta": "Jake borrows Leslie's camera and the lens shatters when it falls on the ground because he fails to zipper the case.When Jake returns the camera, he tells Leslie that he will pay for the repair.", "optb": "Rebecca borrows her neighbor's car, and when she returns it, the gas tank is practically empty. She apologizes profusely and tells her neighbor she will be more considerate the next time.", "optc": "Aaron asks Tom to check in on his apartment while he is out of town. When Tom arrives, he discovers that a pipe has burst and there is a considerable amount of water damage. He calls a plumber to repair the pipe.", "optd": "Lisa suspects that the pothole in her company's parking lot caused her flat tire. She tells her boss that she thinks the company should pay for the repair.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Jake damaged Leslie's camera while it was in his possession and he has agreed to compensate Leslie for the cost of the repair."}, {"question": "Reentry occurs when a person leaves his or her social system for a period of time and then returns. Which situation below best describes Reentry ?", "opta": "When he is offered a better paying position, Jacob leaves the restaurant he manages to manage a new restaurant on the other side of town.", "optb": "Catherine is spending her junior year of college studying abroad in France.", "optc": "Malcolm is readjusting to civilian life after two years of overseas military service.", "optd": "After several miserable months, Sharon decides that she can no longer share an apartment with her roommate Hilary.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Malcolm is the only person returning to a social system that he has been away from for an extended period of time."}, {"question": "Embellishing the Truth occurs when a person adds fictitious details or exaggerates facts or true stories. Which situation below is the best example of Embellishing the Truth?", "opta": "Isabel goes to the theater, and the next day, she tells her coworkers she thought the play was excellent.", "optb": "The realtor describes the house, which is eleven blocks away from the ocean, as prime waterfront property.", "optc": "During the job interview, Fred, who has been teaching elementary school for ten years, describes himself as a very experienced teacher.", "optd": "The basketball coach says it is likely that only the most talented players will get a college scholarship.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The realtor is using a clear exaggeration when she states that a house which is eleven blocks away from the ocean is prime waterfront property."}, {"question": "Establishing a Power of Attorney occurs when a legal document is created that gives one individual the authority to act for another. Which situation below is the best example of Establishing a Power of Attorney?", "opta": "Louise is selling her house and she hires a lawyer to review the contract.", "optb": "Simone's mother can no longer get to the bank to cash her checks and make deposits, so she has taken legal steps to enable Simone to do these things for her.", "optc": "Jack's father is elderly and Jack thinks he is no longer able to make decisions for himself.", "optd": "At her daughter's urging, Mrs.Lenox opens up a retirement account with the local bank.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Simone's mother has taken legal steps to allow another person to act on her behalf. Therefore, this is the only choice that indicates that a power of attorney has been established."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 2, 1, (1/2), (1/4), ... What number should come next?", "opta": "(1/3)", "optb": "(1/8)", "optc": "(2/8)", "optd": "(1/16)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "This is a simple division series; each number is one-half of the previous number.\nIn other terms to say, the number is divided by 2 successively to get the next result.\n\n4/2 = 2\n2/2 = 1\n1/2 = 1/2\n(1/2)/2 = 1/4\n(1/4)/2 = 1/8 and so on."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 7, 10, 8, 11, 9, 12, ... What number should come next?", "opta": "7", "optb": "10", "optc": "12", "optd": "13", "ans": "B", "explanation": "This is a simple alternating addition and subtraction series. In the first pattern, 3 is added; in the second, 2 is subtracted."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 36, 34, 30, 28, 24, ... What number should come next?", "opta": "20", "optb": "22", "optc": "23", "optd": "26", "ans": "B", "explanation": "This is an alternating number subtraction series. First, 2 is subtracted, then 4, then 2, and so on."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 22, 21, 23, 22, 24, 23, ... What number should come next?", "opta": "22", "optb": "24", "optc": "25", "optd": "26", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In this simple alternating subtraction and addition series; 1 is subtracted, then 2 is added, and so on."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 53, 53, 40, 40, 27, 27, ... What number should come next?", "opta": "12", "optb": "14", "optc": "27", "optd": "53", "ans": "B", "explanation": "In this series, each number is repeated, then 13 is subtracted to arrive at the next number."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 21, 9, 21, 11, 21, 13, 21, ... What number should come next?", "opta": "14", "optb": "15", "optc": "21", "optd": "23", "ans": "B", "explanation": "In this alternating repetition series, the random number 21 is interpolated every other number into an otherwise simple addition series that increases by 2, beginning with the number 9."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 58, 52, 46, 40, 34, ... What number should come next?", "opta": "26", "optb": "28", "optc": "30", "optd": "32", "ans": "B", "explanation": "This is a simple subtraction series. Each number is 6 less than the previous number."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 3, 4, 7, 8, 11, 12, ... What number should come next?", "opta": "7", "optb": "10", "optc": "14", "optd": "15", "ans": "D", "explanation": "This alternating addition series begins with 3; then 1 is added to give 4; then 3 is added to give 7; then 1 is added, and so on."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 8, 22, 8, 28, 8, ... What number should come next?", "opta": "9", "optb": "29", "optc": "32", "optd": "34", "ans": "D", "explanation": "This is a simple addition series with a random number, 8, interpolated as every other number. In the series, 6 is added to each number except 8, to arrive at the next number."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 31, 29, 24, 22, 17, ... What number should come next?", "opta": "15", "optb": "14", "optc": "13", "optd": "12", "ans": "A", "explanation": "This is a simple alternating subtraction series, which subtracts 2, then 5."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 1.5, 2.3, 3.1, 3.9, ... What number should come next?", "opta": "4.2", "optb": "4.4", "optc": "4.7", "optd": "5.1", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In this simple addition series, each number increases by 0.8."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 14, 28, 20, 40, 32, 64, ... What number should come next?", "opta": "52", "optb": "56", "optc": "96", "optd": "128", "ans": "B", "explanation": "This is an alternating multiplication and subtracting  series: First, multiply by 2 and then subtract 8."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, ... What number should come next?", "opta": "11", "optb": "12", "optc": "13", "optd": "14", "ans": "B", "explanation": "This is a simple addition series. Each number increases by 2."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 201, 202, 204, 207, ... What number should come next?", "opta": "205", "optb": "208", "optc": "210", "optd": "211", "ans": "D", "explanation": "In this addition series, 1 is added to the first number; 2 is added to the second number; 3 is added to the third number; 4 is added to the fourth number; and go on."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 544, 509, 474, 439, ... What number should come next?", "opta": "404", "optb": "414", "optc": "420", "optd": "445", "ans": "A", "explanation": "This is a simple subtraction series. Each number is 35 less than the previous number."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 80, 10, 70, 15, 60, ... What number should come next?", "opta": "20", "optb": "25", "optc": "30", "optd": "50", "ans": "A", "explanation": "This is an alternating addition and subtraction series. In the first pattern, 10 is subtracted from each number to arrive at the next. In the second, 5 is added to each number to arrive at the next."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 2, 6, 18, 54, ... What number should come next?", "opta": "108", "optb": "148", "optc": "162", "optd": "216", "ans": "C", "explanation": "This is a simple multiplication series. Each number is 3 times more than the previous number."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 5.2, 4.8, 4.4, 4, ... What number should come next?", "opta": "3", "optb": "3.3", "optc": "3.5", "optd": "3.6", "ans": "D", "explanation": "In this simple subtraction series, each number decreases by 0.4."}, {"question": "Look at this series: 8, 6, 9, 23, 87 , ... What number should come next?", "opta": "128", "optb": "226", "optc": "324", "optd": "429", "ans": "D", "explanation": "8 x 1 - 2 = 6  \n6 x 2 - 3 = 9     \n9 x 3 - 4 = 23    \n23 x 4 - 5 = 87   \n87 x 5 - 6 = 429 ..."}, {"question": "Statement: Should India encourage exports, when most things are insufficient for internal use itself?\nArguments:\n\nYes. We have to earn foreign exchange to pay for our imports.\nNo. Even selective encouragement would lead to shortages.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, India can export only the surplus and that which can be saved after fulfilling its own needs, to pay for its imports. Encouragement to export cannot lead to shortages as it shall provide the resources for imports. So, only argument I holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should all the drugs patented and manufactured in Western countries be first tried out on sample basis before giving licence for sale to general public in India?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Many such drugs require different doses and duration for Indian population and hence it is necessary.\nNo. This is just not feasible and hence cannot be implemented.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, health of the citizens is an issue of major concern for the Government. So, a product like drugs, must be first studied and tested in the Indian context before giving licence for its sale. So, only argument I holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should India make efforts to harness solar energy to fulfil its energy requirements?\nArguments:\n\nYes, Most of the energy sources used at present is exhaustible.\nNo. Harnessing solar energy requires a lot of capital, which India lacks in.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, harnessing solar energy will be helpful as it is an inexhaustible resource unlike other resources. So, argument I holds. But argument II is vague as solar energy is the cheapest form of energy."}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be students union in college/university?\nArguments:\n\nNo. This will create a political atmosphere in the campus.\nYes, it is very necessary Students are future political leaders.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The students union formation shall be a step towards giving to students the basic education in the field of politics. However, it shall create the same political atmosphere in the campus. Thus, both the arguments hold strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should India give away Kashmir to Pakistan?\nArguments:\n\nNo. Kashmir is a beautiful state. It earns a lot of foreign exchange for India.\nYes. This would help settle conflicts.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, India cannot part with a state that is a major foreign exchange earner to it. So, argument I holds strong. Further, giving away a piece of land unconditionally and unreasonably is no solution to settle disputes. So, argument II is vague."}, {"question": "Statement: Should cottage industries be encouraged in rural areas?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Rural people are creative.\nYes. This would help to solve the problem of unemployment to some extent.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, cottage industries need to be promoted to create more job opportunities for rural people in the villages themselves. The reason that rural people are creative is vague. So, only argument II holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should young entrepreneurs be encouraged?\nArguments:\n\nYes. They will help in industrial development of the country.\nYes. They will reduce the burden on employment market.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, encouraging the young entrepreneurs will open up the field for the establishment of new industries. Thus, it shall help in industrial development and not only employ the entrepreneurs but create more job opportunities for others as well. So, both the arguments hold strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should all the annual examinations up to Std. V be abolished?\nArguments:\n\nYes. The young students should not be burdened with such examinations which hampers their natural growth.\nNo. The students will not study seriously as they will get automatic promotion to the next class and this will affect them in future.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, neither the students can be burdened with studies at such a tender age, nor can they be left free to take studies casually, as this shall weaken their basic foundation. So, both the arguments follow."}, {"question": "Statement: Should Indian scientists working abroad be called back to India?\nArguments:\n\nYes. They must serve the motherland first and forget about discoveries, honours, facilities and all.\nNo. We have enough talent; let them stay where they want.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Clearly, every person must be free to work wherever he wants and no compulsion should be made to confine one to one's own country. So, argument I is vague. However, talented scientists can be of great benefit to the nation and some alternatives as special incentives or better prospects may be made available to them to retain them within their motherland. So, argument II also does not hold."}, {"question": "Statement: Should we scrap the system of formal education beyond graduation?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It will mean taking employment at an early date.\nNo. It will mean lack of depth of knowledge.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, argument I is vague because at present too, many fields are open to all after graduation. However, eliminating the post-graduate courses would abolish higher and specialized studies which lead to understanding things better and deeply. So, argument II is valid."}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be an upper age limit of 65 years for contesting Parliamentary/ Legislative Assembly elections?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Generally, people above the age of 65 lose their dynamism and will power.\nNo. The life span is so increased that people remain physically and mentally active even up to the age of 80.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The age of a person is no criterion for judging his mental capabilities and administrative qualities. So, none of the arguments holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should new big industries be started in Mumbai?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It will create job opportunities.\nNo. It will further add to the pollution of the city.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Opening up of new industries is advantageous in opening more employment avenues, and disadvantageous in that it adds to the pollution. So, either of the arguments holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should high chimneys be installed in industries?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It reduces pollution at ground level.\nNo. It increases pollution in upper atmosphere.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Pollution at ground level is the most hazardous in the way of being injurious to human and animal life. So, argument I alone holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Does India need so many plans for development?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Nothing can be achieved without proper planning.\nNo. Too much time, money and energy is wasted on planning.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Before indulging in new development programme it is much necessary to plan the exact target, policies and their implementation and the allocation of funds which shows the right direction to work. So, argument I holds strong. Also, planning ensures full utilization of available resources and funds and stepwise approach towards the target. So, spending a part of money on it is no wastage. Thus, argument II is not valid."}, {"question": "Statement: Should articles of only deserving authors be allowed to be published?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It will save a lot of paper which is in short supply.\nNo. It is not possible to draw a line between the deserving and the undeserving.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, I does not provide a strong reason in support of the statement. Also, it is not possible to analyze the really deserving and not deserving. So/argument II holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should colleges be given the status of a university in India?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Colleges are in a better position to assess the student's performance and therefore the degrees will be more valid.\nNo. It is Utopian to think that there will not be nepotism and corruption in awarding degrees by colleges.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Clearly, at the college level, all the students are assessed according to their performance in the University Exams and not on the basis of any criteria of a more intimate dealings with the students. So, argument I is vague. Also, at this level the awarding of degrees is impartial and simply based on his performance. So, argument II also does not hold."}, {"question": "Statement: Should the prestigious people who have committed crime unknowingly, be met with special treatment?\nArguments:\n\nYes. The prestigious people do not commit crime intentionally.\nNo. It is our policy that everybody is equal before the law.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The Constitution of India has laid down the doctrine of 'equality before the law'. So, argument II holds strong. Also, we cannot judge the intentions of a person behind committing a crime, So, argument I is vague."}, {"question": "Statement: Can pollution be controlled?\nArguments:\n\nYes. If everyone realizes the hazards it may create and cooperates to get rid of it, pollution may be controlled.\nNo. The crowded highways, factories and industries and an ever-growing population eager to acquire more and more land for constructing houses are beyond control.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The control of pollution, on one hand, seems to be impossible because of the ever-growing needs and the disconcern of the people but, on the other hand, the control is possible by a joint effort. So, either of the arguments will hold strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should the railways in India be privatized in a phased manner like other public sector enterprises?\nArguments:\n\nYes. This is the only way to bring in competitiveness and provide better services to the public.\nNo. This will pose a threat to the national security of our country as multinationals will enter into the fray.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Privatization would no doubt lead to better services. But saying that this is the 'only way' is wrong. So, argument I does not hold. Argument II also seems to be vague."}, {"question": "Statement: Should internal assessment in colleges be abolished?\nArguments:\n\nYes. This will help in reducing the possibility of favouritism.\nNo, teaching faculty will lose control over students.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Abolishing the internal assessment would surely reduce favouritism on personal grounds because the teachers would not be involved in examination system so that they cannot extend personal benefits to anyone. So, argument I holds strong. But it will not affect the control of teaching faculty on students because still the teachers would be teaching them. So, argument II is vague."}, {"question": "Statement: Should all the unauthorized structures in the city be demolished?\nArguments:\n\nNo. Where will the people residing in such houses live?\nYes. This will give a clear message to general public and they will refrain from constructing unauthorized buildings.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The demolition of unauthorized buildings would teach a lesson to the unscrupulous builders and also serve as a warning for the citizens not to indulge in such activities in the future. This is essential, as unauthorized constructions impose undue burden on the city's infrastructure. So, only argument II holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be a maximum limit for the number of ministers in the Central Government?\nArguments:\n\nNo. The political party in power should have the freedom to decide the number of ministers to be appointed.\nYes. The number of ministers should be restricted to a certain percentage of the total number of seats in the parliament to avoid unnecessary expenditure.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, there should be some norms regarding the number of ministers in the Government, as more number of ministers would unnecessarily add to the Government expenditure. So, argument II holds strong; Also, giving liberty to the party in power could promote extension of unreasonable favour to some people at the cost of government funds. So, argument I does not hold."}, {"question": "Statement: Should foreign films be banned in India?\nArguments:\n\nYes. They depict an alien culture which adversely affects our values.\nNo. Foreign films are of a high artistic standard.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Clearly, foreign films depict the alien culture but this only helps in learning more. So, argument I does not hold. Also, the reason stated in argument II is not strong enough in contradicting the ban. So, it also does not hold."}, {"question": "Statement: Is buying things on instalments profitable to the customer?\nArguments:\n\nYes. He has to pay less.\nNo, paying instalments upsets the family budget.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "In buying things on instalments, a customer has to pay more as the interest is also included. So, argument I does not hold. Moreover, one who buys an item on instalments maintains his future budget accordingly as he is well acquainted with when and how much he has to pay, beforehand. So, argument II is also not valid."}, {"question": "Statement: Should Doordarshan be given autonomous status?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It will help Doordarshan to have fair and impartial coverage of all important events.\nNo. The coverage of events will be decided by a few who may not have healthy outlook.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, the autonomous status of the Doordarshan will be a step towards giving it independence for an impartial coverage. Autonomous status does not mean that the coverage will be decided by a few. So, only argument I holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should adult education programme be given priority over compulsory education programme?\nArguments:\n\nNo. It will also help in success of compulsory education programme.\nYes. It will help to eliminate the adult illiteracy.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, argument I gives a reason in support of the statement and so it does not hold strong against it. The adult education programme needs to be given priority because it shall eliminate adult illiteracy and thus help in further spread of education. So, only argument II is strong enough."}, {"question": "Statement: Should new universities be established in India?\nArguments:\n\nNo. We have still not achieved the target for literacy.\nNo. We will have to face the problem of unemployed but highly qualified people.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, instead of improving upon higher education, increasing the literacy rate should be heeded first. So, argument I holds. Also, more number of universities will produce more degree holders with the number of jobs remaining the same, thus increasing unemployment. So, argument II also holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should non-vegetarian food be totally banned in our country?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It is expensive and therefore it is beyond the means of most people in our country.\nNo. Nothing should be banned in a democratic country like ours.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, restriction on the diet of people will be denying them their basic human right. So, only argument II holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should a total ban be put on trapping wild animals?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Trappers are making a lot of money;\nNo. Bans on hunting and trapping are not effective.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Clearly, ban is necessary to protect our natural environment. So, none of the arguments is strong enough."}, {"question": "Statement: Should Government close down loss-making public sector enterprises?\nArguments:\n\nNo. All employees will lose their jobs, security and earning, what would they do?\nYes. In a competitive world the rule is 'survival of the fittest'.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Closing down public-sector enterprises will definitely throw the engaged persons out of employment. So, argument I holds. Also, closing down is no solution for a loss-making enterprise. Rather, its causes of failure should be studied, analyzed and the essential reforms implemented. Even if this does not work out, the enterprise may be privatized. So, argument II is vague,"}, {"question": "Statement: Should government jobs in rural areas have more incentives?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Incentives are essential for attracting government servants there.\nNo. Rural areas are already cheaper, healthier and less complex than big cities. So ? Why offer extra incentives!", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, government jobs in rural areas are underlined with several difficulties. In  lieu of these, extra incentives are needed. So, only argument I holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be a cap on maximum number of contestants for parliamentary elections in any constituency?\nArguments:\n\nYes. This will make the parliamentary elections more meaningful as the voters can make a considered judgement for casting their vote.\nNo. In a democracy any person fulfilling the eligibility criteria can contest parliamentary elections and there should be no restrictions.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, if there were less candidates, the voters would find it easy to make a choice. So, argument I holds. Also, every person satisfying the conditions laid down by the Constitution must be given an opportunity and should not be denied the same just to cut down the number of candidates. So, argument II also holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should so much money be spent on advertisements?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It is an essential concomitant in a capitalist economy.\nNo. It leads to wastage of resources.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, the advertisements are/the means to introduce people with the product and its advantages. So, argument I holds strong. But argument II is vague because advertisements are an investment for better gain and not a, wastage."}, {"question": "Statement: Should all the legislators be forced to resign from their profession?\nArguments:\n\nYes. They will be able to devote more time for the country.\nNo, nobody will contest election.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The legislators should surely not be engaged in any other profession because only then will they be able to work with devotion. So, argument I holds. Also, if such a law is enforced, only those people will contest elections who are really prepared to work for the country. So, argument II is vague."}, {"question": "Statement: Should 'computer knowledge' be made a compulsory subject for all the students at secondary school level?\nArguments:\n\nNo, our need is 'bread' for everyone, we cannot follow western models.\nYes. We cannot compete in the international market without equipping our children with computers.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Nowadays, computers have entered all walks of life and children need to be prepared for the same. So, argument II is strong. Argument I holds no relevance."}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be uniforms for students in the colleges in India as in the schools?\nArguments:\n\nYes, this will improve the ambience of the colleges as all the students will be decently dressed.\nNo. The college students should not be regimented and they should be left to choose their clothes for coming to the college.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, after being in strict discipline and following a formal dress code of the school for so many years, the students must be granted some liberty in college life, as they have to take on the responsibilities of life, next. Besides, schools adopt uniforms to take care of the security of the child - an aspect which doesn't matter much in the colleges. So, argument II holds strong. Also, the environment of the college depends on the students' dedication and etiquettes and not on their uniforms. So, argument I is vague."}, {"question": "Statement: Should India engage into a dialogue with neighbouring countries to stop cross border tension?\nArguments:\n\nYes. This is the only way to reduce the cross border terrorism and stop loss of innocent lives.\nNo. Neighbouring countries cannot be relied upon in such matters, they may still engage in subversive activities.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, peaceful settlement through mutual agreement is the best option, whatever be the issue. So, argument I holds strong. Moreover, the problem indicated in II can be curbed by constant check and vigilance. So, II seems to be vague."}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be a world government?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It will help in eliminating tensions among the nations.\nNo. Then, only the developed countries will dominate in the government.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, a world government cannot eliminate tensions among nations because it will also have the ruling group and the opposition group. Further, the more powerful and diplomatic shall rule the world to their interests. So, only argument II holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should the practice of transfers of clerical cadre employees from government offices of one city to those of another be stopped?\nArguments:\n\nNo. Transfer of employees is a routine administrative matter and we must continue it.\nYes. It involves lot of governmental expenditure and inconvenience too many compared to the benefits it yields.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "It is not necessary that any practice which has been in vogue for a long time is right and it must be continued. So, argument I is not strong. Also, a practice must be continued or discontinued in view of its merits/demerits and not on grounds of the expenditure or procedures it entails. The policy of transfer is generally practised to do away with corruption, which is absolutely essential. So, argument II also does not hold."}, {"question": "Statement: Is paying ransom or agreeing to the conditions of kidnappers of political figures, a proper course of action?\nArguments:\n\nYes. The victims must be saved at all cost.\nNo. It encourages the kidnappers to continue their sinister activities.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Both the arguments are strong enough. The conditions have to be agreed to, in order to save the life of the victims, though actually they ought not to be agreed to, as they encourage the sinister activities of the kidnappers."}, {"question": "Statement: Should religion be banned?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It develops fanaticism in people.\nNo, Religion binds people together.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Religion binds people together through the name of God and human values. But at the same time it may create differences and ill-will among people. So, either of the arguments holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should India become a permanent member of UN's Security Council?\nArguments:\n\nYes. India has emerged as a country which loves peace and amity.\nNo. Let us first solve problems of our own people like poverty, malnutrition.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "A peace-loving nation like India can well join an international forum which seeks to bring different nations on friendly terms with each other. So, argument I holds strong. Argument II highlights a different aspect. The internal problems of a nation should not debar it from strengthening international ties. So, argument II is vague."}, {"question": "Statement: Should fashionable dresses be banned?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Fashions keep changing and hence consumption of cloth increases.\nNo. Fashionable clothes are a person's self expression and therefore his/her fundamental right.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, imposing ban on fashionable dresses will be a restriction on the personal choice and hence the right to freedom of an individual. So, only argument II is strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should an organization like UNO be dissolved?\nArguments:\n\nYes. With cold war coming to an end, such organizations have no role to play\nNo, In the absence of such organizations there may be a world war.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "An organization like UNO is meant to maintain peace all over and will always serve to prevent conflicts between countries. So, its role never ends. So, argument I does not hold. Also, lack of such an organization may in future lead to increased mutual conflicts and international wars, on account of lack of a common platform for mutual discussions. So, argument II holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be no place of interview in selection?\nArguments:\n\nYes, it is very subjective in assessment.\nNo. It is the only instrument to judge candidates' motives and personality.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, besides interview, there can be other modes of written examination to judge candidates' motives. So argument II is not strong enough. However, the interview is a subjective assessment without doubt. So, argument I holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should family planning be made compulsory in India?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Looking to the miserable conditions in India, there is no other go.\nNo. In India there are people of various religions and family planning is against the tenets of some of the religions.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Family planning is an essential step to curb population growth. So, argument I holds strong. Also, family planning being against the tenets of some of the Indian religions, it is not necessary to make it compulsory. Instead, it can be enforced by creating public awareness of the benefits of family planning. So, argument II also holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should income tax be abolished in India?\nArguments:\n\nYes. It is an unnecessary burden on the wage earners.\nNo. It is a good source of revenue.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Income -tax is levied so that every citizen can contribute a share of his earning towards the infrastructural development of the nation. So, argument I seems to be vague. However, income-tax is no doubt a good source of revenue for the government. Hence, argument II holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be a ceiling on the salary of top executives of multinationals in our country?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Otherwise it would lead to unhealthy competition and our own industry would not be able to withstand that.\nNo. With the accent on liberalization of economy, any such move would be counter-productive. Once the economy picks up, this disparity will be reduced.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "E", "explanation": "In the absence of such a ceiling, the companies would be involved in a mutual competition of salaries, in a bid to attract the most competent professionals. So, argument I holds. Also, the prospects of increase in salary would encourage the officials to perform better in the interest of the company they serve, which would otherwise not be so if a ceiling is imposed. So, argument II also holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should school education be made free in India?\nArguments:\n\nYes. This is the only way to improve the level of literacy.\nNo. It would add to the already heavy burden on the exchequer.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Making education free for all is not the only means to ensure literacy. An awareness needs to be aroused for this. So, argument I is vague. Also, such a step would require immense funds and lead to financial drain. So, argument II holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should import duty on all the electronic goods be dispensed with?\nArguments:\n\nNo. This will considerably reduce the income of the government and will adversely affect the developmental activities.\nNo. The local manufacturers will not be able to compete with the foreign manufacturers who are technologically far superior.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Abolishing the import duty on electronic goods shall reduce the costs of imported goods and adversely affect the sale of the domestic products, thus giving a setback to the Indian electronics industry. So, argument II holds strong. Argument I does not provide a convincing reason."}, {"question": "Statement: Should children be legally made responsible to take care of their parents during their old age?\nArguments:\n\nYes. Such matter can only be solved by legal means.\nYes. Only this will bring some relief to poor parents.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Taking care of the parents is a moral duty of the children and cannot be thrust upon them legally, nor such a compulsion can ensure good care of the old people. So, none of the arguments holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be reservation in Government jobs for candidates from single child family?\nArguments:\n\nNo. This is not advisable as the jobs should be offered to only deserving candidates without any reservation for a particular group.\nYes. This will help reduce the growing population in India as the parents will be encouraged to adopt single child norm.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The Government has already made provisions for reservation of jobs for the economically backward sections, which is a must. So, abolishing the practice of reservation altogether has no meaning. Thus, argument I is vague. Also, more reservations would lead to non-recruitment of many more deserving candidates. Besides, such a reservation, if  implemented, will cater to the job requirements of only a small section of population and not a major part of it. So, argument II also does not hold strong."}, {"question": "Statement: Should higher education be completely stopped for some time?\nArguments:\n\nNo. It will hamper the country's future progress.\nYes. It will reduce the educated unemployment.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, higher education is not the cause of unemployment. In fact, it has created greater job opportunities. So, argument II is vague. Also, higher education promotes the country's development. So, argument I holds."}, {"question": "Statement: Should we scrap the 'Public Distribution System' in India?\nArguments:\n\nYes, Protectionism is over, everyone must get the bread on his/her own.\nYes. The poor do not get any benefit because of corruption.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The Public Distribution System is indeed necessary to provide basic amenities to the economically backward sections of population. So, argument I is vague. Also, if the Objectives of a system are not fulfilled because of corruption, then getting rid of the system is no solution. Instead, efforts should be made to end corruption and extend its benefits to the people for whom it is meant. So, argument II also does not hold,"}, {"question": "Statement: Should India have no military force at all?\nArguments:\n\nNo. Other countries in the world do not believe in non-violence.\nYes. Many Indians believe in non-violence.", "opta": "Only argument I is strong", "optb": "Only argument II is strong", "optc": "Either I or II is strong", "optd": "Neither I nor II is strong", "opte": "Both I and II are strong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Clearly, India needs to have military force to defend itself against the threat of other military powers in the world. So, none of the arguments holds strong."}, {"question": "Statement:  \"You are hereby appointed as a programmer with a probation period of one year and your performance will be reviewed at the end of the period for confirmation.\" - A line in an appointment letter.\nAssumptions:\n\nThe performance of an individual generally is not known at the time of appointment offer.\nGenerally an individual tries to prove his worth in the probation period.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The performance of the individual has to be tested over a span of time as the statement mentions. So, I is implicit. The statement mentions that the individual's worth shall be reviewed (during probation period) before confirmation. So, II is also implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  It is desirable to put the child in school at the age of 5 or so.\nAssumptions:\n\nAt that age the child reaches appropriate level of development and is ready to learn.\nThe schools do not admit children after six years of age.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since the statement talks of putting the child in school at the age of 5, it means that the child is mentally prepared for the same at this age. So, I is implicit. But nothing about admission after 6 years of age is mentioned in the statement. So, II is not implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  \"In order to bring punctuality in our office, we must provide conveyance allowance to our employees.\" - In charge of a company tells Personnel Manager.\nAssumptions:\n\nConveyance allowance will not help in bringing punctuality.\nDiscipline and reward should always go hand in hand.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Assumption I goes against the statement. So, it is not implicit. The allowance will serve as a reward to the employees and shall provoke them to come on time. So, II is implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Unemployment allowance should be given to all unemployed Indian youth above 18 years of age.\nAssumptions:\n\nThere are unemployed youth in India who needs monetary support.\nThe government has sufficient funds to provide allowance to all unemployed youth.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "I directly follows from the statement and so is implicit. Also, the statement is a suggestion and does not tell about a government policy or its position of funds. So, II is not implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  \"If you trouble me, I will slap you.\" - A mother warns her child.\nAssumptions:\n\nWith the warning, the child may stop troubling her.\nAll children are basically naughty.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The mother warns her child with the expectation that he would stop troubling her. So, I is implicit. The general nature of children cannot be derived from the statement. So, II is not implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  The State government has decided to appoint four thousand primary school teachers during the next financial year.\nAssumptions:\n\nThere are enough schools in the state to accommodate four thousand additional primary school teachers.\nThe eligible candidates may not be interested to apply as the government may not finally appoint such a large number of primary school teachers.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Such decisions as given in the statement are taken only after taking the existing vacancies into consideration. So, I implicit while II isn't."}, {"question": "Statement:  A warning in a train compartment - \"To stop train, pull chain. Penalty for improper use Rs. 500.\"\nAssumptions:\n\nSome people misuse the alarm chain.\nOn certain occasions, people may want to stop a running train.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, the penalty is imposed to prevent people from misusing the alarm chain. This means that some people misuse it. So, I is implicit. The alarm chain is provided to stop the running train in times of urgency. So, II is also implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  If it is easy to become an engineer, I don't want to be an engineer.\nAssumptions:\n\nAn individual aspires to be professional.\nOne desires to achieve a thing which is hard earned.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, nothing is mentioned about the professional nature of the job. So, I is not implicit. The statement hints that one rejects a thing that is easy to achieve. So, II is implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  The concession in rail fares for the journey to hill stations has been cancelled because it is not needed for people who can spend their holidays there.\nAssumptions:\n\nRailways should give concession only to needy persons.\nRailways should not encourage people to spend their holidays at hill stations.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The statement mentions that concessions should not be given to people who can afford to spend holidays in hill stations. This means they should be given only to needy persons. So, I is implicit. But, II does not follow from the statement and is not implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  \"The bridge was built at the cost of Rs. 128 crores and even civil bus service is not utilizing it, what a pity to see it grossly underutilized.\" - A citizen's view on a new flyover linking east and west sides of a suburb.\nAssumptions:\n\nThe building of such bridges does not serve any public objective.\nThere has to be some accountability and utility of money spent on public projects.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, the statement expresses grave concern over a newly-built flyover not being utilized by public. This implies that such projects need to be taken up only after working out their utility and that the huge expenditure incurred on building such structures is worthwhile only if they prove useful for the public. Thus, only II is implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  The Government has decided to levy 2 percent on the tax amount payable for funding drought relief programmes.\nAssumptions:\n\nThe Government does not have sufficient money to fund drought relief programmes.\nThe amount collected by way of surcharge may be adequate to fund these drought relief programmes.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Since a surcharge has been levied to fund drought relief programmes, it follows that the Government does not have sufficient money for the same. So, I is implicit. Besides, the percentage of surcharge must have been decided after studying the expected inflow in relation to amount of funds required. So, II is also implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Detergents should be used to clean clothes.\nAssumptions:\n\nDetergents form more lather.\nDetergents help to dislodge grease and dirt.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Nothing is mentioned about lather formation by the detergent. So, I is not implicit. Also, detergents should be used as they clean clothes better and more easily. So, II is implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  It will be a substantial achievement in the field of education if one provides one school for every village in our country and enforce attendance.\nAssumptions:\n\nChildren in villages do not attend school regularly.\nProviding school to every village is desirable.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The statement lays stress on enforcing attendance. This implies that children in villages do not attend school regularly. So, I is implicit. Besides, the statement calls 'one school for every village' a 'substantial achievement'. So, II is also implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  The government has decided to disinvest large chunk of its equity in select public sector undertakings for a better fiscal management.\nAssumptions:\n\nThe amount generated out of the disinvestment process may reduce substantially the mounting fiscal deficits.\nThere will be enough demand in the market for the shares of these undertakings.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The fact given in I directly follows from the phrase '..... for a better fiscal management' in the statement. So, I is implicit. However, the public response to the new policy cannot be ascertained. So, II is not implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Never before such a lucid book was available on the topic.\nAssumptions:\n\nSome other books were available on this topic.\nYou can write lucid books on very few topics.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "It follows from the statement that books on this topic were available before also but they were not 'lucid'. So, I is implicit. But a general comment as II cannot be made from the given statement. So, II is not implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Please do not use lift while going down - an instruction on the top floor of a five-storey building.\nAssumptions:\n\nWhile going down, the lift is unable to carry any load.\nProvision of lift is a matter of facility and not of right.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The statement requests people not to use lift while moving down. This implies that the lift may be used to move up and the request has been made so that more people can use the lift for ascending which would otherwise cause more physical stress than going down the stairs. So, only II is implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  \"I have not received telephone bills for nine months inspite of several complaints\" - A telephone customer's letter to the editor of a daily\nAssumptions:\n\nEvery customer has a right to get bills regularly from the telephone company.\nThe customer's complaints point to defect in the services which are expected to be corrected.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The customer's eagerness to get the bills makes I implicit. Besides, the customer has written to the editor to bring the malfunctioning of the department to public notice. So, II is also implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  \"This drink can be had either as it is, or after adding ice to it.\" - An advertisement.\nAssumptions:\n\nPeople differ in their preferences.\nSome people will get attracted to the drink as it can be had as it is.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The advertisement tells the different ways in which the drink can be had. This means that different people prefer to have it in a different way and that some people would prefer it only because it can be taken in a particular manner. So, both I and II are implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Government has permitted unaided colleges to increase their fees.\nAssumptions:\n\nUnaided colleges are in financial difficulties.\nAided colleges do not need to increase fees.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Unaided colleges have been allowed to increase their fees. This means that they are in financial difficulties. So, I is implicit. Nothing is mentioned about the aided colleges. So, II is not implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Be humble even after being victorious.\nAssumptions:\n\nMany people are humble after being victorious.\nGenerally people are not humble.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, nothing is mentioned about the nature of the people. So, I is not implicit. Also, the statement gives an advice of being humble even after being victorious. This means that generally people are not humble. So, II is implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  The government has decided to pay compensation to the tune of Rs. 1 lakh to the family members of those who are killed in railway accidents.\nAssumptions:\n\nThe government has enough funds to meet the expenses due to compensation.\nThere may be reduction in incidents of railway accidents in near future.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, the amount of compensation must have been decided keeping in mind the monetary position of the Government. So, I is implicit. However, nothing can be said about the frequency of railway accidents in future. So, II is not implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Films have become indispensable for the entertainment of people.\nAssumptions:\n\nFilms are the only media of entertainment.\nPeople enjoy films.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "B", "explanation": "'Films are indispensable' does not mean that they are the only means of entertainment. So, I is not implicit. Clearly, II follows from the statement. So, it is implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Of all the newspapers published in Mumbai, readership of the \"Times\" is the largest in the Metropolis.\nAssumptions:\n\n'Times' is not popular in mofussil areas.\n'Times' has the popular feature of cartoons on burning social and political issues.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Neither the volume of readership of the 'Times' in areas other than the Metropolis nor the reason for its huge acclamation is evident from the statement So, neither I  nor II is implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Apart from the entertainment value of television, its educational value cannot be ignored.\nAssumptions:\n\nPeople take television to be a means of entertainment only.\nThe educational value of television is not realised properly.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The statement makes the first assumption clear though educational value is not to be ignored. So, I is implicit. That the educational value must not be ignored also shows that educational value is not realised properly. So, II is also implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Children are influenced more by their teachers nowadays.\nAssumptions:\n\nThe children consider teachers as their models.\nA large amount of children's time is spent in school.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, it is because children consider teachers as their model that they are more influenced by them. So, I is implicit. It is not necessary that the children are influenced by teachers because they spend much time in school. So, II is not implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  You know that your suit is excellent when people ask about your tailor who tailored the suit.\nAssumptions:\n\nPeople do not ask about your tailor if your suit is not good.\nThe people want to know the criterion of an excellent suit.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The statement mentions that if the people ask about the tailor, your suit is good. This means that people ask only in the situation when the thing is good. So, I is implicit. The criteria of an excellent suit is not mentioned. So, II is not implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  His recent investment in the shares of Company A is only a gamble.\nAssumptions:\n\nHe may incur loss on his investment.\nHe may gain from his investment.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The use of the world 'gamble' indicates that he may either gain or lose in the deal."}, {"question": "Statement:  Why don't you go to the court if the employer does not pay you the Provident Fund contribution?\nAssumptions:\n\nCourts can intervene in matters of dispute between employer and employees.\nIt is obligatory for the employer to pay the Provident Fund contribution to the employees.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, the statement encourages one to go to court to get his Provident Fund from his employer. This implies that the issue comes under the jurisdiction of courts and that it is the right of the employee to claim his Provident Fund. So, both I and II are implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  'Double your money in five months.' - An advertisement.\nAssumptions:\n\nThe assurance is not genuine.\nPeople want their money to grow.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The truth or falsity of the promise made in the statement cannot be judged. So, I is not implicit. Since the concerned firm advertises with the assurance that money can be doubled quickly by investing with it, so II is implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  The education of a student at collegiate level, not taking into account maintenance expenses, costs four hundred rupees a year. Collegiate education is thus drawing heavily upon the national resources of an impoverished community. So college education should be restricted to a brilliant few.\nAssumptions:\n\nOur resources are very limited.\nOnly a few students should be admitted to the colleges.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The use of the words 'impoverished community' in the statement makes I implicit while the phrase 'college education should be restricted to a brilliant few' makes II implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  A's advice to B - \"Go to Jammu via Amritsar - the shortest route\".\nAssumptions:\n\nB wishes to go to Jammu.\nA gives advice to everybody.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "A has advised B the route to Jammu. This means that B wishes to go to Jammu. So, I is implicit. The statement mentions only A's advice to B. So, II is not implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  All existing inequalities can be reduced, if not utterly eradicated, by action of governments or by revolutionary change of government.\nAssumptions:\n\nInequality is a man-made phenomenon.\nNo person would voluntarily part with what he possesses.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since inequality can be reduced, it means that it is not natural but created. So, I is implicit. Nothing is mentioned about people's response. So, II is not implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  The campaign of 'Keep your city clean' started by the Civil Council did not evoke any response from the citizens.\nAssumptions:\n\nPeople do not desire to keep their city clean.\nThe Civil Council has failed in its campaign.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "E", "explanation": "According to the statement, the campaign did not get any response from citizens. This means that people are not interested in keeping the city clean and the campaign has failed. So, both I and II are implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  The district administration has issued a circular to all the farmers under its jurisdiction advising them for not using pesticides indiscriminately as it may pollute the ground water.\nAssumptions:\n\nPeople may stop using ground water if the farmers continue to use pesticides indiscriminately.\nFarmers may refrain from using pesticides indiscriminately.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The district administration has issued a circular to make the farmers aware of hazards that indiscriminate use of pesticides poses to ground water and plead them to refrain from the same. So, II is implicit. However, I cannot be assumed from the given statement and so it is not implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  The coffee powder of company X is quite better in taste than the much advertised coffee of company Y.\nAssumptions:\n\nIf your product is not good, your spend more on advertisement.\nSome people are tempted to buy a product by the advertisement.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since the statement holds the product of company X more superior in quality than that of Y which spends more on advertisement, so I is not implicit. According to the statement, the product of company Y is more known because of more advertisement. So, II is implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Of all the radio sets manufactured in India, the 'X' brand has the largest sale.\nAssumptions:\n\nThe sale of all the radio sets manufactured in India is known.\nThe manufacturing of no other radio set in India is as large as 'X' brand radio.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, the comparison could not be made without knowing the sale of all the radio sets. So, I is implicit. The statement mentions only that the sale is largest and nothing is mentioned about the manufacture. So, II is not implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  \"You should not grant him leave in this week due to exigency of work.\" - A supervisor advises the administrative officer.\nAssumptions:\n\nRequest for leave can be turned down also.\nThe supervisor has reviewed the work required to be done during the said period.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The advice is given to turn down the request for leave. So, I is implicit. The mention of the 'exigency of work' makes II implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Like a mad man, I decided to follow him.\nAssumptions:\n\nI am not a mad man.\nI am a mad man.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The words 'Like a mad man' show that either a person is really mad or he is not mad but acted like mad. So, either I or II is implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  The first step in treating addicts is to re-establish their lost ties, for which a continuous personal attention should be paid to the addicts under treatment.\nAssumptions:\n\nAddicts under treatment respond better when shown personal interest.\nAddiction and strained relationships are intimately connected.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, treatment of addiction requires personal attention as the first step. So, I is implicit. Also, since intimacy and personal attention are required to treat addicts, it implies that addiction arises out of frustration due to strained relationships. So, II is also implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Beware of dogs, our dogs do not bark, but they are trained to distinguish between genuine guests and intruders.\nAssumptions:\n\nBarking dogs bite rarely.\nOur dogs could be dangerous for intruders.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The statement clearly warns the visitors to beware of dogs as they are trained to welcome the guests and intruders differently. So, II is implicit. I is vague and hence, it is not implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Because of the large number of potholes in road X, reaching airport in time has become difficult.\nAssumptions:\n\nReaching airport in time may not be always necessary.\nThere is no other convenient road to the airport.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The statement presents the issue of 'not reaching airport in time' as a problem. This means that reaching airport in time is necessary. So, I is not implicit. Besides, it is mentioned that reaching airport in time has become difficult due to large number of potholes in road X. This implies that road X is the only possible way. So, II is implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Safety and health practices in many Indian companies are well below the international standards.\nAssumptions:\n\nInternational standards of health and safety are ideal and unrealistic.\nIndian organizations do not consider safety and health management as their prime social responsibility.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The statement talks about the safety and health practices in Indian companies being far below international standards. It is clearly a criticism of Indian organizations not paying considerable attention to these aspects. So, II is implicit. The international standards demand perfection and are, in no way, non-achievable. So, I is not implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Greater public participation results in good civic governance. - Statement of Municipal Commissioner of City A.\nAssumptions:\n\nThe municipal office is not competent to effect good civic administration.\nGood civic governance is a matter of collective will and effort of the people and administration.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The statement stresses on the fact that though civic governance is the task of the municipal body, but all the tasks done come out to be more fruitful if the general public lends a helping hand in the same. So, only II is implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  The regulatory authority has set up a review committee to find out the reasons for unstable stock prices.\nAssumptions:\n\nThe investors may regain confidence in stock market by this decision.\nThe review committee has the expertise to find out the causes for volatility in the stock market.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, I mentions the aim for which the step talked about in the statement, has been undertaken while II mentions the essential requirement for it. So, both I and II  are implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Please note that the company will provide accommodation to only outside candidates if selected.' - A condition in an advertisement.\nAssumptions:\n\nThe local candidates would be having some other arrangement for their stay.\nThe company plans to select only local candidates.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The statement mentions that the company intends to provide accommodation only to outside candidates. This means that local candidates would have to arrange accommodation on their own and that the company may select local as well as outside candidates. Thus, only I is implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Cases of food poisoning due to consumption of liquor are increasing in rural areas.\nAssumptions:\n\nPercentage of people consuming liquor is more in rural areas.\nThere are many unauthorized spurious liquor shops in the rural areas.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The statement talks of number of cases of food poisoning due to consumption of liquor and not of the number of cases consuming liquor. So, I is not implicit. Besides, the statement indicates that people in rural areas are getting spurious or low-grade liquor and no check is being kept on shops selling liquor there. So, II is implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Lack of stimulation in the first four or five years of life can have adverse consequences.\nAssumptions:\n\nA great part of the development of observed intelligence occurs in the earliest years of life\n50 percent of the measurable intelligence at age of 17 is already predictable by the age of four.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The lacking in first four or five years can be adverse because it is the main period of development. So, I is implicit. Since nothing is mentioned about the predictability of intelligence, II is not implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  The X-Airlines has decided to increase the passenger fare by 15 percent with immediate effect.\nAssumptions:\n\nThe demand for seats of X-Airlines may remain unchanged even after the hike of fare.\nOther airline companies may also hike the passenger fares.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, such decisions are taken only after making sure that it will not affect the company's business adversely. So, I is implicit. However, the impact of this increase on other airlines cannot be ascertained. So, II is not implicit."}, {"question": "Statement:  Shalini made an application to the bank for a loan of Rs. 1,80,000 by mortgaging her house to the bank and promised to repay it within five years.\nAssumptions:\n\nThe bank has a practice of granting loans for Rs. 1,00,000 and above.\nThe bank accepts house as collateral security against such loans.", "opta": "Only assumption I is implicit", "optb": "Only assumption II is implicit", "optc": "Either I or II is implicit", "optd": "Neither I nor II is implicit", "opte": "Both I and II are implicit", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The fact that Shalini has applied for a loan of Rs. 1,80,000 implies that the bank can grant a loan above Rs. 1,00,000. So, I is implicit. II also follows directly from the statement and so is implicit."}, {"question": "Statements: In a one day cricket match, the total runs made by a team were 200. Out of these 160 runs were made by spinners.\nConclusions:\n\n80% of the team consists of spinners.\nThe opening batsmen were spinners.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "According to the statement, 80% of the total runs were made by spinners. So, I does not follow. Nothing about the opening batsmen is mentioned in the statement. So, II also does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: The old order changed yielding place to new.\nConclusions:\n\nChange is the law of nature.\nDiscard old ideas because they are old.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, I directly follows from the given statement. Also, it is mentioned that old ideas are replaced by new ones, as thinking changes with the progressing time. So, II does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: Government has spoiled many top ranking financial institutions by appointing bureaucrats as Directors of these institutions.\nConclusions:\n\nGovernment should appoint Directors of the financial institutes taking into consideration the expertise of the person in the area of finance.\nThe Director of the financial institute should have expertise commensurate with the financial work carried out by the institute.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "According to the statement, Government has spoiled financial institutions by appointing bureaucrats as Directors. This means that only those persons should be appointed as Directors who are experts in finance and are acquainted with the financial work of the institute. So, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statements: Population increase coupled with depleting resources is going to be the scenario of many developing countries in days to come.\nConclusions:\n\nThe population of developing countries will not continue to increase in future.\nIt will be very difficult for the governments of developing countries to provide its people decent quality of life.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The fact given in I is quite contrary to the given statement. So, I does not follow. II mentions the direct implications of the state discussed in the statement. Thus, II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Prime age school-going children in urban India have now become avid as well as more regular viewers of television, even in households without a TV. As a result there has been an alarming decline in the extent of readership of newspapers.\nConclusions:\n\nMethod of increasing the readership of newspapers should be devised. \nA team of experts should be sent to other countries to study the impact of TV. on the readership of newspapers.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The statement concentrates on the increasing viewership of TV. and does not stress either on increasing the readership of newspapers or making studies regarding the same. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: In Japan, the incidence of stomach cancer is very high, while that of bowel cancer is very low. But Japanese immigrate to Hawaii, this is reversed - the rate of bowel cancer increases but the rate of stomach cancer is reduced in the next generation. All this is related to nutrition - the diets of Japanese in Hawaii are different than those in Japan.\nConclusions:\n\nThe same diet as in Hawaii should be propagated in Japan also.\nBowel cancer is less severe than stomach cancer.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The statement neither propagates the diet of any of the countries nor compares the two types of cancer. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: The Government run company had asked its employees to declare their income and assets but it has been strongly resisted by employees union and no employee is going to declare his income.\nConclusions:\n\nThe employees of this company do not seem to have any additional undisclosed income besides their salary.\nThe employees union wants all senior officers to declare their income first.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Nothing about the details of the employees' income or the cause of their refusal to declare their income and assets, can be deduced from the given statement. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Monitoring has become an integral part in the planning of social development programmes. It is recommended that Management Information System be developed for all programmes. This is likely to give a feedback on the performance of the functionaries and the efficacy with which services are being delivered.\nConclusions:\n\nAll the social development programmes should be evaluated.\nThere is a need to monitor the performance of workers.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "According to the statement, monitoring and evaluation of social development programmes - their function, performance and efficiency - is absolutely essential. So, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statements: The T.V. programmes, telecast specially for women are packed with a variety of recipes and household hints. A major portion of magazines for women also contains the items mentioned above.\nConclusions:\n\nWomen are not interested in other things.\nAn average woman's primary interest lies in home and specially in the kitchen.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, nothing about 'other things' is mentioned in the statement. So, I does not follow, Also, since it is mentioned that programmes and magazines for women are stuffed with kitchen recipes and other household hints, it means that women have special interest in these areas. So, II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: The distance of 900 km by road between Bombay and Jafra will be reduced to 280 km by sea. This will lead to a saving of Rs. 7.92 crores per annum on fuel. \nConclusions:\n\nTransportation by sea is cheaper than that by road.\nFuel must be saved to the greatest extent", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "According to the statement, sea transport is cheaper than road transport in the case of route from Bombay to Jafra, not in all the cases. So, conclusion I does not follow. The statement stresses on the saving of fuel. So, conclusion II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: The manager humiliated Sachin in the presence of his colleagues.\nConclusions:\n\nThe manager did not like Sachin.\nSachin was not popular with his colleagues.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The manager might have humiliated Sachin not because of his dislike but on account of certain negligence or mistake on his part. So, I does not follow. Also, nothing about Sachin's rapport with his colleagues can be deduced from the statement. So, II also does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: Women's organisations in India have welcomed the amendment of the Industrial Employment Rules 1946 to curb sexual harassment at the work place.\nConclusions:\n\nSexual harassment of women at work place is more prevalent in India as compared to other developed countries.\nMany organisations in India will stop recruiting women to avoid such problems.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The fact that a certain rule has been more welcomed in a certain country does not imply that the problem is more prevalent there. So, I does not follow. Also, the amendment seeks to discourage only sexual harassment of women and shall in no way discourage employment of women. So, II also does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: Nation X faced growing international opposition for its decision to explode eight nuclear weapons at its test site.\nConclusions:\n\nThe citizens of the nation favoured the decision.\nSome powerful countries do not want other nations to become as powerful as they are.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Neither the citizens response to the decision nor the reason for opposition by other nations can be deduced from the statement. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: In a highly centralised power structure, in which even senior cabinet ministers are prepared to reduce themselves to pathetic countries or yesmen airing views that are primarily intended to anticipate or reflect the Prime Minister's own performances, there can be no place for any consensus that is quite different from real or contrived unanimity of opinion, expressed through a well orchestrated endorsement of the leader's actions.\nConclusions:\n\nThe Ministers play safe by not giving anti-government views.\nThe Prime Minister does not encourage his colleagues to render their own views.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "According to the statement, even senior cabinet ministers are always ready to conform to the Prime Minister's views. So, I follows. However, II contradicts the given statement and so does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: National Aluminium Company has moved India from a position of shortage to self-sufficiency in the metal.\nConclusions:\n\nPreviously, India had to import aluminium.\nWith this speed, it can soon become a foreign exchange earner.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "According to the statement, National Aluminium Company has moved India from a position of shortage in the past to self-sufficiency in the present. This means that previously, India had to import aluminium. So, I follows. Also, it can be deduced that if production increases at the same rate, India can export it in future. So, II also follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Jade plant has thick leaves and it requires little water.\nConclusions:\n\nAll plants with thick leaves require little water.\nJade plants may be grown in places where water is not in abundance.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The statement talks of jade plants only and not 'all plants with thick leaves'. So, I does not follow. Also, since jade plants require little water, so they can be grown in places where water is not in abundance. So, II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Use \"Kraft\" colours. They add colour to our life. - An advertisement.\nConclusions:\n\nCatchy slogans do not attract people.\nPeople like dark colours.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The slogan given in the statement is definitely a catchy one which indicates that catchy slogans do attract people. So, I does not follow. Nothing about people's preference for colours can be deduced from the statement. Thus, II also does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: All those political prisoners were released on bail who had gone to jail for reasons other than political dharnas. Bail was not granted to persons involved in murders.\nConclusions:\n\nNo political - prisoner had committed murder.\nSome politicians were not arrested.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "According to the statement, the political prisoners can be divided into two groups - those who were released and those who were put in jail for political dharnas. However, no person involved in murder was released. This means that no political prisoner had committed murder. So, I follows. Clearly, II is not directly related to the statement and does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: Modern man influences his destiny by the choice he makes unlike in the past.\nConclusions:\n\nEarlier there were fewer options available to man.\nThere was no desire in the past to influence the destiny.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, I directly follows from the statement while II cannot be deduced from it."}, {"question": "Statements: Water supply in wards A and B of the city will be affected by about 50% on Friday because repairing work of the main lines is to be carried out.\nConclusions:\n\nThe residents in these wards should economise on water on Friday.\nThe residents in these wards should store some water on the previous day.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, the information has been given beforehand so that the residents can collect water on the previous day and use less water on Friday. So, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statements: People who speak too much against dowry are those who had taken it themselves.\nConclusions:\n\nIt is easier said than done.\nPeople have double standards.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The statement clearly implies that it is easier to say than to do something and what people say is different from what they do. So, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statements: The national norm is 100 beds per thousand populations but in this state, 150 beds per thousand are available in the hospitals.\nConclusions:\n\nOur national norm is appropriate.\nThe state's health system is taking adequate care in this regard.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Whether the national norm is appropriate or not cannot be said. So, I does not follow. However, more number of beds per thousand population are available in the state. So, II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Our securities investments carry market risk. Consult your investment advisor or agent before investing.\nConclusions:\n\nOne should not invest in securities.\nThe investment advisor calculates the market risk with certainty.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Investment in securities involves risk. This does not mean that one should not invest in securities. So, I does not follow. Since the statement advises one to consult investment advisor before investing, so II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Money plays a vital role in politics.\nConclusions:\n\nThe poor can never become politicians.\nAll the rich men take part in politics.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Neither the poor nor the rich, but only the role of money in politics is being talked about in the statement. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Vegetable prices are soaring in the market.\nConclusions:\n\nVegetables are becoming a rare commodity.\nPeople cannot eat vegetables.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The availability of vegetables is not mentioned in the given statement. So, I does not follow Also, II is not directly related to the statement and so it also does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: The serious accident in which a person was run down by a car yesterday had again focused attention on the most unsatisfactory state of roads.\nConclusions:\n\nThe accident that occurred was fatal.\nSeveral accidents have so far taken place because of unsatisfactory state of roads.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Since the accident has caused concern, it must be fatal. So, I follows. The use of the word 'again' in the statement justifies the fact mentioned in II. So, II also follows."}, {"question": "Statements: In a recent survey report, it has been stated that those who undertake physical exercise for at least half an hour a day are less prone to have any heart ailments.\nConclusions:\n\nModerate level of physical exercise is necessary for leading a healthy life.\nAll people who do desk-bound jobs definitely suffer from heart ailments.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The statement mentions that chances of heart ailments are greatly reduced by a regular half-hour exercise. So, I follows. However, it talks of only reducing the probability which does not mean that persons involved in sedentary jobs shall definitely suffer from heart ailments. So, II does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: A bird in hand is worth two in the bush.\nConclusions:\n\nWe should be content with what we have.\nWe should not crave for what is not.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Both the given conclusions clearly bring out the central theme of the proverb given in the statement. So, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statements: This world is neither good nor evil; each man manufactures a world for himself.\nConclusions:\n\nSome people find this world quite good.\nSome people find this world quite bad.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The statement mentions that the world for a man is as he makes it himself. So, some people might find it good and some quite bad. Thus, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statements: The eligibility for admission to the course is minimum second class Master's degree. However, the candidates who have appeared for the final year examination of Master's degree can also apply.\nConclusions:\n\nAll candidates who have yet to get their Master's degree will be there in the list of selected candidates.\nAll candidates having obtained second class Master's degree will be there in the list of selected candidates.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The statement mentions that the candidates who have obtained second class Master's degree or have appeared for the final year examination of Master's degree, can apply for admission. This implies that both types of candidates may be selected on certain grounds. Thus, some candidates of each type and not all candidates of any one type, may be selected. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Any student who does not behave properly while in the school brings bad name to himself and also for the school.\nConclusions:\n\nSuch student should be removed from the school.\nStricter discipline does not improve behaviour of the students.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Clearly, I cannot be deduced from the statement. Also, nothing about discipline is mentioned in the statement. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: A Corporate General Manager asked four managers to either submit their resignations by the next day or face termination orders from service. Three of them had submitted their resignations by that evening.\nConclusions:\n\nThe next day, the remaining manager would also resign.\nThe General Manager would terminate his services the next day.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "C", "explanation": "It is mentioned in the statement that either the managers should resign by the next day or their services would be terminated. So, either I or II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Only good singers are invited in the conference. No one without sweet voice is a good singer.\nConclusions:\n\nAll invited singers in the conference have sweet voice. \nThose singers who do not have sweet voice are not invited in the conference.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The statement asserts that a good singer always has a sweet voice and only good singers are invited in the conference. This implies that all those invited in the conference have sweet voice and those who do not have sweet voice are not invited. So, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statements: To cultivate interest in reading, the school has made it compulsory from June this year for each student to read two books per week and submit a weekly report on the books.\nConclusions:\n\nInterest in reading can be created by force.\nSome students will eventually develop interest in reading.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, the new scheme intends to develop interest in reading by incorporating the habit in their routine. So, only II follows while I does not."}, {"question": "Statements: Applications of applicants who do no fulfil eligibility criteria and/or who do not submit applications before last date will be summarily rejected and will not be called for the written test.\nConclusions:\n\nThose who are called for the written test are those who fulfil eligibility criteria and have submitted their applications before last date.\nWritten test will be held only after scrutiny of applications.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The statement clearly mentions that fulfilling the eligibility criteria and submitting the application before the stipulated date are both essential to avoid rejection. So, I follows. Also, since it is given that the candidates whose applications are rejected shall not be called for written test, so II also follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Recent trends also indicate that the number of child migrants in large cities is increasing. These children leave their families to join the ranks of urban poor doing odd jobs in markets, workshops, hotels or in service sectors.\nConclusions:\n\nMigration to big cities should be checked. \nThe plight of poor children should be thoroughly studied.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The statement mentions the problem of increased migration of children to cities. But the ways to deal with the problem cannot be deduced from it. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: No country is absolutely self-dependent these days.\nConclusions:\n\nIt is impossible to grow and produce all that a country needs.\nCountrymen in general have become lazy.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, only I provides a suitable explanation to the given statement. So, only I follows."}, {"question": "Statements: The percentage of the national income shared by the top 10 per cent of households in India is 35.\nConclusions:\n\nWhen an economy grows fast, concentration of wealth in certain pockets of population takes place. \nThe national income is unevenly distributed in India.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Nothing about the growth of economy is mentioned in the statement. So, I does not follow. Also, it is given that 35 per cent of national income is shared by 10 per cent of households. This indicates unequal distribution. So, II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Players who break various records in a fair way get special prizes. Player X broke the world record but was found to be under the influence of a prohibited drug.\nConclusions:\n\nX will get the special prize.\nX will not get the special prize.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, X will not get the special prize because although he broke the world record, he was found to use unfair means. So, II follows while I does not."}, {"question": "Statements: Company X has marketed the product. Go ahead; purchase it if price and quality are your considerations.\nConclusions:\n\nThe product must be good in quality.\nThe price of the product must be reasonable.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "It is mentioned in the statement that one who considers price and quality before buying a product should buy the product of company X. So, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statements: Quality has a price tag. India is allocating lots of funds to education.\nConclusions:\n\nQuality of education in India would improve soon.\nFunding alone can enhance quality of education.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "According to the statement, funding is necessary to improve quality and India is allocating funds to education. This means that quality of education will improve in India. So, I follows. But funding alone is sufficient to enhance quality, is not true. So, II does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: Although we have rating agencies like Crisil, ICRA, there is demand to have a separate rating agency for IT companies to protect investors.\nConclusions:\n\nAssessment of financial worth of IT companies calls for separate set of skills, insight and competencies. \nNow the investors investing in IT companies will get protection of their investment.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The need for separate rating agency for IT companies clearly indicates that such assessment requires a separate set of skills. So, I follows. However, the statement indicates only the need or demand and neither the future course of action nor its after-effects can be judged. So, II does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: The standard of education in private schools is much better than Municipal and Zila Parishad-run schools.\nConclusions:\n\nThe Municipal and Zila Pariskad should make serious efforts to improve standard of their schools.\nAll Municipal and Zila Parishad schools should be closed immediately.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, the solution to the problem is not to close down the Municipal and Zila Parishad-run schools but to strive to improve the standard of education of these schools. So, only I follows while II does not."}, {"question": "Statements: All the organised persons find time for rest. Sunita, in spite of her very busy schedule, finds time for rest.\nConclusions:\n\nSunita is an organised person.\nSunita is an industrious person.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Sunita has a very busy schedule. This means that she is industrious. But still she finds time for rest. This means that she is an organised person. So, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statements: Domestic demand has been increasing faster than the production of indigenous crude oil.\nConclusions:\n\nCrude oil must be imported.\nDomestic demand should be reduced.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The statement mentions that demand for oil is increasing faster than the production. So, either the demand must be reduced or oil must be imported to cope with the increasing demand. Thus, either I or II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: He stressed the need to stop the present examination system and its replacement by other methods which would measure the real merit of the students.\nConclusions:\n\nExaminations should be abolished.\nThe present examination system does not measure the real merit of the students.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The statement stresses the need to adopt a new method of examination. So, I does not follow. However, II directly follows from the given statement."}, {"question": "Statements: Fashion is a form of ugliness so intolerable that we have to alter it every six months.\nConclusions:\n\nFashion designers do not understand the public mind very well.\nThe public by and large is highly susceptible to novelty.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The statement asserts that people cannot stand any particular trend for long and seek change quite often. So, only II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Until our country achieves economic equality, political freedom and democracy would be meaningless.\nConclusions:\n\nPolitical freedom and democracy go hand in hand.\nEconomic equality leads to real political freedom and democracy.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Nothing about the relation between political freedom and democracy is mentioned in the statement. So, I does not follow. But II directly follows from the given statement."}, {"question": "The attainment of individual and organisational goals is mutually interdependent and linked by a common denominator - employee work motivation. Organisational members are motivated to satisfy their personal goals, and they contribute their efforts to the attainment of organisational objectives as means of achieving these personal goals. The passage best supports the statement that motivation -", "opta": "encourages an individual to give priority to personal goals over organisational goals.", "optb": "is crucial for the survival of an individual and organisation.", "optc": "is the product of an individual's physical and mental energy.", "optd": "is the external force which induces an individual to contribute his efforts.", "opte": "makes organisation and society inseparable.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Due to enormous profits involved in smuggling, hundreds of persons have been attracted towards this anti-national activity. Some of them became millionaires overnight. India has a vast coastline both on the Eastern and Western Coast. It has been a heaven for smugglers who have been carrying on their activities with great impunity. There is no  doubt, that from time to time certain seizures were made by the enforcement authorities, during raids and ambush but even allowing these losses the smugglers made huge profits. The passage best supports the statement that", "opta": "smuggling hampers the economic development of a nation.", "optb": "smuggling ought to be curbed.", "optc": "authorities are taking strict measures to curb smuggling.", "optd": "smuggling is fast increasing in our country owing to the quick profit it entails.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Though the waste of time or the expenditure on fashions is very large, yet fashions have come to stay. They will not go, come what may. However, what is now required is that strong efforts should be made to displace the excessive craze for fashion from the minds of these youngsters. The passage best supports the statement that:", "opta": "fashion is the need of the day.", "optb": "the excessive craze for fashion is detrimental to one's personality.", "optc": "the hoard for fashion should be done away with so as not to let down the constructive development.", "optd": "work and other activities should be valued more than the outward appearance.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One of the important humanitarian by-products of technology is the greater dignity and value that it imparts to human labour. In a highly industrialized society, there is no essential difference between Brahmin and Dalit, Muslim and Hindu; they are equally useful and hence equally valuable for in the industrial society individual productivity fixes the size of the pay cheque and this fixes social status. The passage best supports the statement that:", "opta": "technology decides individual's social status.", "optb": "castes and religions are man-made.", "optc": "human labour has dignity and value.", "optd": "all individuals, irrespective of caste and creed, are born equal.", "opte": "industrial society is a great leveller of men.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The future of women in India is quite bright and let us hope that they will justify their abilities by rising to the occasion. Napoleon was right when he declared that by educating the women we can educate the whole nation. Because a country can never rise without the contribution of 50% of their population. The passage best supports the statement that:", "opta": "India is striving hard for the emancipation of women.", "optb": "all women should be well educated.", "optc": "a nation can progress only when women are given equal rights and opportunities as men.", "optd": "women ought to be imparted full freedom to prove their worth and contribute to the progress of the nation.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The prevention of accidents makes it necessary not only that safety devices be used to guard exposed machinery but also that mechanics be instructed in safety rules which they must follow for their own protection, and that lighting in the plant be adequate. The passage best supports the statement that industrial accidents -", "opta": "are always avoidable;", "optb": "may be due to ignorance.", "optc": "cannot be entirely overcome.", "optd": "can be eliminated with the help of safety rules.", "opte": "usually result from inadequate machinery.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To forgive an injury is often considered to be a sign of weakness; it is really a sign of strength. It is easy to allow oneself to be carried away by resentment and hate into an act of vengeance; but it takes a strong character to restrain those natural passions. The man who forgives an injury proves himself to be the superior of the man who wronged himself and puts the wrong-doer to shame. The passage best supports' the statement that:", "opta": "the sufferer alone knows the intensity of his sufferings.", "optb": "people tend to forgive the things happened in the past.", "optc": "natural passions are difficult to suppress.", "optd": "mercy is the noblest form of revenge.", "opte": "a person with calm and composed nature has depth of thought and vision.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Industrial exhibitions play a major role in a country's economy. Such exhibitions, now regularly held in Delhi, enable us to measure the extent of our own less advanced industrial progress and the mighty industrial power and progress of countries like the U.K., U.S.A. and Russia whose pavilions are the centres of the greatest attention and attractions. The passage best supports the statement that industrial exhibitions -", "opta": "greatly tax the poor economies.", "optb": "are more useful for the developed countries like U.S.A. whose products stand out superior to those of the developing countries.", "optc": "are not of much use to the countries who are industrially backward.", "optd": "boost up production qualitatively and quantitatively by analytical comparison of a country's products with those of the developed countries.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The school has always been the most important means of transferring the wealth of tradition form one generation to the next. This applies today in an even higher degree than in former times for, through the modern development of economy, the family as bearer of tradition and education has become weakened. This passage best supports the statement that for transferring the wealth of tradition from one generation to the next  -", "opta": "there are means other than the school.", "optb": "several different sources must be tried.", "optc": "economic development plays a crucial role", "optd": "modern technology must be put to use.", "opte": "family, as ever, is the most potent means.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Emerson said that the poet was landlord, Sealord, airlord. The flight of imagination made the poet master of land, sea and air. But a poet's dream of yesterday becomes today an actual achievement and a reality for all men. Even those who invented, improved and perfected the aeroplane could hardly have dreamt of the possibility of flight into outer space. The passage best supports the statement that:", "opta": "seemingly impossible imaginations make one a good poet,", "optb": "all imaginations become a reality some day.", "optc": "what man imagined has never been impossible; he has always turned it a reality through his conception of ideas and sheer hard labour.", "optd": "man has reached the climax of technological development with his exploration into outer space.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It is up to our government and planners to devise ways and means for the mobilisation of about ten crore workers whose families total up about forty crore men, women and children. Our agriculture is over-manned. A lesser number of agriculturists would mean more purchasing or spending power to every agriculturist. This will result in the shortage of man-power for many commodities to be produced for which there will be a new demand from a prosperous agrarian class. This shortage will be removed by surplus man-power released from agriculture as suggested above. The passage best supports the statement that:", "opta": "employment in production is more fruitful than employment in agriculture.", "optb": "Indian economy is in a poor shape basically due to improper mobilisation of man-power.", "optc": "a shift of labour from agricultural sector to the industrial sector would uplift the living standard.", "optd": "the industrial sector is labour-deficient while the agricultural sector is over-manned in our country.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Exports and imports, a swelling favourable balance of trade, investments and bank-balances, are not an index or a balance sheet of national prosperity. Till the beginning of the Second World War, English exports were noticeably greater than what they are today. And yet England has greater national prosperity today than it ever had. Because the income of average Englishmen, working as field and factory labourers, clerks, policemen, petty shopkeepers and shop assistants, domestic workers and other low-paid workers, has gone up. The passage best supports the statement that:", "opta": "a country's economic standard can be best adjudged by per capital income.", "optb": "a country's balance of trade is the main criteria of determining its economic prosperity.", "optc": "a nation's economy strengthens with the increase in exports.", "optd": "English trade has continually increased since the Second World War.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Satisfaction with co-workers, promotion opportunities, the nature of work, and pay goes with high performance among those with strong growth needs. Among those with weak growth needs, no such relationship is present - and, in fact, satisfaction with promotion opportunities goes with low performance. This passage best supports the statement that:", "opta": "satisfaction is an inevitable organisational variable.", "optb": "job satisfaction and performance are directly and closely related.", "optc": "relationship between job satisfaction and performance is moderated by growth need.", "optd": "every organisation has few employees having weak growth need.", "opte": "high performance is essential for organisational effectiveness.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The only true education comes through the stimulation of the child's powers by the demands of the social situations in which he finds himself. Through these demands he is stimulated to act as a member of a unity, to emerge from his original narrowness of action and feeling, and to conceive himself from the standpoint of the welfare of the group to which he belongs. The passage best supports the statement that real education -", "opta": "will take place if the children imbibe action and feeling.", "optb": "will take place if the children are physically strong.", "optc": "is not provided in our schools today.", "optd": "comes through the interaction with social situations.", "opte": "comes from the self-centred approach of the students.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The press should not be afraid of upholding and supporting a just and righteous cause. It should not be afraid of criticising the government in a healthy manner. The press has to be eternally vigilant to protect the rights of the workers, backward and suppressed sections of the society. It should also give a balanced view of the things so that people can be helped in the formation of a healthy public opinion. The passage best supports the statement that", "opta": "press has a great role to play in a democracy.", "optb": "the press is the only means to project to the masses the policies of the government.", "optc": "the freedom of press is essential for the proper functioning of democracy.", "optd": "the press can be used by the governments as an effective media for the upliftment of the backward sections of society.", "opte": "all the information given by the press should be well-articulated so as to gain a good opinion towards the ruling party.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Throughout the ages the businessman has helped build civilisation's great cities, provided people with luxuries and artists with patronage, and lift his fellow citizens to understand the standard of living. In the last few centuries the businessman has seeded the Industrial Revolution around the world.  The passage best supports the statement that the businessman -", "opta": "is accountable to the society.", "optb": "lives luxurious and comfortable life.", "optc": "is the beneficiary of the Industrial Revolution.", "optd": "is capable of raising his standard of living.", "opte": "has contributed to the growth of civilisation.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "There is a shift in our economy from a manufacturing to a service orientation. The increase in service-sector will require the managers to work more with people rather than with objects and things from the assembly line. This passage best supports the statement that:", "opta": "managers should have a balanced mind.", "optb": "assembly line will exist in service organisations.", "optc": "interpersonal skills will become more important in the future work place.", "optd": "manufacturing organisations ignore importance of people.", "opte": "service organisations will not deal with objects and things.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The virtue of art does not allow the work to be interfered with or immediately ruled by anything other than itself. It insists that it alone shall touch the work in order to bring it into being. Art requires that nothing shall attain the work except through art itself. This passage best supports the statement that:", "opta": "art is governed by external rules and conditions.", "optb": "art is for the sake of art and life.", "optc": "art is for the sake of art alone.", "optd": "artist realises his dreams through his artistic creation.", "opte": "artist should use his art for the sake of society.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "opta": "parsley", "optb": "basil", "optc": "dill", "optd": "mayonnaise", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Parsley, basil, and dill are types of herbs. Mayonnaise is not an herb."}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "opta": "inch", "optb": "ounce", "optc": "centimeter", "optd": "yard", "ans": "B", "explanation": "An ounce measures weight; the other choices measure length."}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "opta": "tyre", "optb": "steering wheel", "optc": "engine", "optd": "car", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Tyre, steering wheel, and engine are all parts of a car."}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "opta": "tulip", "optb": "rose", "optc": "bud", "optd": "daisy", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Tulip, rose, and daisy are all types of flowers. A bud is not."}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "opta": "rye", "optb": "sourdough", "optc": "pumpernickel", "optd": "loaf", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Loaf, sourdough, and pumpernickel are types of bread. A rye is not a bread type.\nLoaf - Bread that is shaped and baked in one piece and usually sliced before being eaten.\nPumpernickel - Dark, dense German bread made from coarsely ground whole-grain rye.\nSourdough - Leaven for making bread, consisting of fermenting dough, typically that left over from a previous batch.\nRye - A wheatlike cereal plant that tolerates poor soils and low temperatures."}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "opta": "guitar", "optb": "flute", "optc": "violin", "optd": "cello", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The guitar, violin, and cello are stringed instruments; the flute is a wind instrument."}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "opta": "dodge", "optb": "flee", "optc": "duck", "optd": "avoid", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Dodge, duck, and avoid are all synonyms meaning evade. Flee means to run away from."}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "opta": "branch", "optb": "dirt", "optc": "leaf", "optd": "root", "ans": "B", "explanation": "A branch, leaf, and root are all parts of a tree. The dirt underneath is not a part of the tree."}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "opta": "street", "optb": "freeway", "optc": "interstate", "optd": "expressway", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Freeway, interstate, and expressway are all high- speed highways; a street is for low-speed traffic."}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "opta": "heading", "optb": "body", "optc": "letter", "optd": "closing", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Heading, body, and closing are all parts of a letter;  the letter is the whole, not a part."}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "opta": "tape", "optb": "twine", "optc": "cord", "optd": "yarn", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The yarn, twine, and cord are all used for tying. The tape is not used in the same way."}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "opta": "leopard", "optb": "cougar", "optc": "elephant", "optd": "lion", "ans": "C", "explanation": "A leopard, cougar, and lion all belong to the cat family; an elephant does not."}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "opta": "couch", "optb": "rug", "optc": "table", "optd": "chair", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The couch, table, and chair are pieces of furniture; the rug is not."}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "opta": "cornea", "optb": "retina", "optc": "pupil", "optd": "vision", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The cornea, retina, and pupil are all parts of the eye."}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "opta": "noun", "optb": "preposition", "optc": "punctuation", "optd": "adverb", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The noun, preposition, and adverb are classes of words that make up a sentence. Punctuation belongs in a sentence, but punctuation is not a class of word."}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "opta": "book", "optb": "index", "optc": "glossary", "optd": "chapter", "ans": "A", "explanation": "An index, glossary, and chapter are all parts of a book. Choice a does not belong because the book is the whole, not a part."}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "opta": "unimportant", "optb": "trivial", "optc": "insignificant", "optd": "familiar", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The first three choices are all synonyms."}, {"question": "Vincent has a paper route. Each morning, he delivers 37 newspapers to customers in his neighborhood. It takes Vincent 50 minutes to deliver all the papers. If Vincent is sick or has other plans, his friend Thomas, who lives on the same street, will sometimes deliver the papers for him.", "opta": "Vincent and Thomas live in the same neighborhood.", "optb": "It takes Thomas more than 50 minutes to deliver the papers.", "optc": "It is dark outside when Vincent begins his deliveries.", "optd": "Thomas would like to have his own paper route.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The fact that Vincent and Thomas live on the same street indicates that they live in the same neighborhood. There is no support for any of the other choices."}, {"question": "The Pacific yew is an evergreen tree that grows in the Pacific Northwest. The Pacific yew has a fleshy, poisonous fruit. Recently, taxol, a substance found in the bark of the Pacific yew, was discovered to be a promising new anticancer drug.", "opta": "Taxol is poisonous when taken by healthy people.", "optb": "Taxol has cured people from various diseases.", "optc": "People should not eat the fruit of the Pacific yew.", "optd": "The Pacific yew was considered worthless until taxol was discovered.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Given the information presented, the only statement that could be considered true is that the fruit should not be eaten because it is poisonous. There is no support that taxol is poisonous or that taxol has cured anyone (choices a and b). There is no support for choice d."}, {"question": "Erin is twelve years old. For three years, she has been asking her parents for a dog. Her parents have told her that they believe a dog would not be happy in an apartment, but they have given her permission to have a bird. Erin has not yet decided what kind of bird she would like to have.", "opta": "Erin's parents like birds better than they like dogs.", "optb": "Erin does not like birds.", "optc": "Erin and her parents live in an apartment.", "optd": "Erin and her parents would like to move.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Since Erin's parents think a dog would not be happy in an apartment, we can reasonably conclude that the family lives in an apartment. We do not know if Erin's parents dislike dogs (choice a) or if Erin  dislikes birds (choice b).There is no support for choice d."}, {"question": "Tim's commute never bothered him because there were always seats available on the train and he was able to spend his 40 minutes comfortably reading the newspaper or catching up on paperwork. Ever since the train schedule changed, the train has been extremely crowded, and by the time the doors open at his station, there isn't a seat to be found.", "opta": "Tim would be better off taking the bus to work.", "optb": "Tim's commute is less comfortable since the train schedule changed.", "optc": "Many commuters will complain about the new train schedule.", "optd": "Tim will likely look for a new job closer to home.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The passage tells us that Tim's commute didn't bother  him because he was always able to sit down and comfortably read or do paperwork. Therefore, it is reasonable to assume that Tim's commute has become less comfortable since the schedule change, because it is very crowded and he can no longer find a seat. There is no information given that supports choices a, c, and d."}, {"question": "When they heard news of the hurricane, Maya and Julian decided to change their vacation plans. Instead of traveling to the island beach resort, they booked a room at a fancy new spa in the mountains. Their plans were a bit more expensive, but they'd heard wonderful things about the spa and they were relieved to find availability on such short notice.", "opta": "Maya and Julian take beach vacations every year.", "optb": "The spa is overpriced.", "optc": "It is usually necessary to book at least six months in advance at the spa.", "optd": "Maya and Julian decided to change their vacation plans because of the hurricane.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The first sentence makes this statement true. There is no support for choice a. The passage tells us that the spa vacation is more expensive than the island beach resort vacation, but that doesn't necessarily mean that the spa is overpriced; therefore, choice b cannot be supported. And even though the paragraph says that the couple was relieved to find a room on short notice, there is no information to support choice c, which says that it is usually necessary to book at the spa at least six months in advance."}, {"question": "Ten new television shows appeared during the month of September. Five of the shows were sitcoms, three were hour-long dramas, and two were news-magazine shows. By January, only seven of these new shows were still on the air. Five of the shows that remained were sitcoms.", "opta": "Only one of the news-magazine shows remained on the air.", "optb": "Only one of the hour-long dramas remained on the air.", "optc": "At least one of the shows that was cancelled was an hour-long drama.", "optd": "Television viewers prefer sitcoms over hour-long dramas.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "If there were seven shows left and five were sitcoms, this means that only two of the shows could possibly be dramas. Choices a and b may be true, but there is no evidence to indicate this as fact. The fact that all of the sitcoms remained does not necessarily mean that viewers prefer sitcoms (choice d)."}, {"question": "On weekends, Mr. Sanchez spends many hours working in his vegetable and flower gardens. Mrs. Sanchez spends her free time reading and listening to classical music. Both Mr. Sanchez and Mrs. Sanchez like to cook.", "opta": "Mr. Sanchez enjoys planting and growing vegetables.", "optb": "Mr. Sanchez does not like classical music.", "optc": "Mrs. Sanchez cooks the vegetables that Mr. Sanchez grows.", "optd": "Mrs. Sanchez enjoys reading nineteenth century novels.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Because Mr. Sanchez spends many hours during the weekend working in his vegetable garden, it is reasonable to suggest that he enjoys this work. There is no information to suggest that he does not like classical music. Although Mrs. Sanchez likes to cook, there is nothing that indicates she cooks vegetables (choice c). Mrs. Sanchez likes to read, but there is no information regarding the types of books she reads (choice d)."}, {"question": "Georgia is older than her cousin Marsha. Marsha's brother Bart is older than Georgia. When Marsha and Bart are visiting with Georgia, all three like to play a game of Monopoly. Marsha wins more often than Georgia does.", "opta": "When he plays Monopoly with Marsha and Georgia, Bart often loses.", "optb": "Of the three, Georgia is the oldest.", "optc": "Georgia hates to lose at Monopoly.", "optd": "Of the three, Marsha is the youngest.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "If Georgia is older than Marsha and Bart is older than Georgia, then Marsha has to be the youngest of the three. Choice b is clearly wrong because Bart is the oldest. There is no information in the paragraph to support either choice a or choice c."}, {"question": "Sara lives in a large city on the East Coast. Her younger cousin Marlee lives in the Mid-west in a small town with fewer than 1,000 residents. Marlee has visited Sara several times during the past five years. In the same period of time, Sara has visited Marlee only once.", "opta": "Marlee likes Sara better than Sara likes Marlee.", "optb": "Sara thinks small towns are boring.", "optc": "Sara is older than Marlee.", "optd": "Marlee wants to move to the East Coast.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Since the paragraph states that Marlee is the younger cousin, Sara must be older than Marlee. There is no information to support the other choices."}]]}